<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id: adminpanel.xml,v 1.2 2002/07/01 21:22:35 hackie Exp $ -->
<chapter id="administrating_fud">
<title>Administrating FUD Forum 2</title>
	<para>
		&FUDforum; is controlled via series of control panels that are 
		readily available to all of the forum's administrators via the "Admin Control Panel" link
		found on nearly every single page of the forum.
	</para>	

	<para>	
		Using these control panels the administrator is able to adjust all of the forum's aspects as well
		manage the forum's files &amp; modify the forum's templates via a convenient template editor.
	</para>

	<sect1 id="admin.forum_consistency">
		<title>Forum Consistency</title>
		
		<para>
			Forum consistency checks the integrity of FUDforum's data and repairs it if any 
			inconsistency is found. This process also regenerates forum caches of various
			data such as moderators, thread views etc... It is highly recommended to run a 
			consistency checker once per month on high traffic forums and once every two or three months
			on low traffic forums.
		</para>
		
		<para>	
			If you see some irregularities with the forum data or inconsistent information being
			displayed, run the consistency checker, in most cases this will resolve the problem.
			
			<note>
			<simpara>
				If the problem persists after running a consistency check, please take
				the time to report it as a bug, by going to the 
				<ulink url="http://fud.prohost.org/forum/"><citetitle>&FUDforum; support forum</citetitle></ulink>
			</simpara>	
			</note>
		</para>
		
		&disabled.warning;
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.rebuild_search_index">
		<title>Rebuild Search Index</title>
		
		<para>
			FUDforum includes a full text search that allows the user to search the 
			messages posted on the forum by both subject and message body. 
		</para>	
		
		<para>
			When a user posts a message the text of that message is automatically added to the 
			search index, unless you've set your <link linkend="global.option.FORUM_SEARCH">FORUM_SEARCH</link> option to no.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The search index rebuild process will go through every message on the forum and re-index it's data
			for the search engine. This process, as you can imagine, is VERY CPU intensive and will take a fair amount
			of time to run. The actual time taken depends on the number of messages you have in your forum.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			This process is generally unnecessary, unless you've decided to re-enable the full text search of the forum
			or have completed an conversion process from a forum other then FUDforum to FUDforum and need to generate
			a search index of the imported messages.
		</para>	

		&disabled.warning;
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.compact_messages">
		<title>Compact Messages</title>
		
		<para>
			FUDforum will try compact it's message storage file. During normal
			operation FUDforum only writes to it's message file, never deletes from it,
			this is done because it has great performance benefits and is a very fast
			way to store message bodies. If you are running low on drive space you
			can try to have FUDforum try to compact it's message file, this will
			try to remove all the old unused bodies off all edited messages.
			
			<note>
				<simpara>
				Unless there is a lot of deletion and message editing on your forum, 
				the amount of space saved will be minimal.
				</simpara>	
			</note>
		</para>
		
		&disabled.warning;
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.global_settings_manager">
		<title>Global Settings Manager</title>
		
		<para>
			This control panel allows you to alter the various system settings of the forum.
			Pay careful attention to what you are doing while making changes on this control panel, 
			since it possible to break your forum by entering wrong values in certain places.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Due to the importance of that control panel there is basic help for every option on the control
			panel itself.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.global_settings_manager.options">
			<title>Global Options</title>
			
			<sect3 id="global.primary.options">
				<title>Primary Forum Options</title>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.FORUM_TITLE">
					<title>Forum Title</title>
				
					<para>
						The title of the forum. The text entered here will appear inside the HTML &lt;title&gt; tag.
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.FORUM_ENABLED">
					<title>Forum Enabled</title>
				
					<para>
						This toggle shows you whether or not your forum is enabled as well as allows you to enable and disable your
						forum.
					</para>
				
					<para>
						When your forum is disabled the users will see the message you put inside <link linkend="global.option.DISABLED_REASON">Disabled Reason</link>
						when they try to access any of the forum's pages.
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.DISABLED_REASON">
					<title>Disabled Reason</title>
				
					<para>
						When your forum is disabled this message, which can contain HTML will be displayed to anyone trying to 
						access the forum's pages.
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.ALLOW_REGISTRATION">
					<title>Allow Registration</title>
				
					<para>
						This toggle allows you to enable or disable new user registration.
					</para>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="global.dir.options">
				<title>Forum Directory Paths</title>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.INCLUDE">
					<title>Include Directory</title>
				
					<para>
						This is where all the compiled forum include files (*.inc) will be placed.
						&user.note;
						&dir.important;
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.WWW_ROOT">
					<title>Your Forum's URL</title>
				
					<para>
						This is the base URL of your forum.
						&user.note;
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.ERROR_PATH">
					<title>Error Directory</title>
				
					<para>
						This is the directory where the forum's error logs will be stored.
						&user.note;
						&dir.important;
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.MSG_STORE_DIR">
					<title>Message Storage Directory</title>
				
					<para>
						Inside this directory the bodies of all message, normal &amp; private are stored.
						&user.note;
						&dir.important;
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.TMP">
					<title>Temporary Directory</title>
					
					<para>
						This is the directory where any temporary forum files will be placed.
						&user.note;
						&dir.important;
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.FILE_STORE">
					<title>File Storage Directory</title>
				
					<para>
						Inside this directory all the file that are attached to forum's messages are stored.
						&user.note;
						&dir.important;
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.FORUM_SETTINGS_PATH">
					<title>Forum Settings Directory</title>
				
					<para>
						Various settings file that are created by the forum are stored inside this directory.
						&user.note;
						&dir.important;
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.MOGRIFY_BIN">
					<title>Path to Mogrify Utility</title>
				
					<para>
						Mogrify is an ImageMagick utility that allows you to manipulate images. If you have such a utility
						specify the full path to it in this option. By doing so, you will gain the ability the scale down 
						user uploaded avatars if they exceed the dimensions you've specified.
					</para>
					
					<note>
						<simpara>
						ImageMagick and its utilities can be downloaded freely from <ulink url="http://www.imagemagick.org/"><citetitle>ImageMagick website</citetitle></ulink>.
						</simpara>
					</note>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="global.db.options">
				<title>Database Settings</title>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.DBHOST">
					<title>Database Server</title>
				
					<para>
						The IP or UNIX Domain Socket of your database server. We recommend using the UNIX Domain Socket 
						since it is much faster then TCP/IP.
						
						<note>
							<simpara>
							If you decide to specify a UNIX Domain Socket you need to put ':' in front of it.
							For example: <literal>:/tmp/mysql.sock</literal>
							</simpara>
						</note>
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.DBHOST_USER">
					<title>Database Login</title>
				
					<para>
						The login name for the database you intend to store forum data in.
					</para>
				
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.DBHOST_PASSWORD">
					<title>Database Password</title>
				
					<para>
						The password for the database you intend to store forum data in.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.DBHOST_DBNAME">
					<title>Database Name</title>
				
					<para>
						The name of the database you intend to use to store your data in.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.DBHOST_PERSIST">
					<title>Use Persistent Connections</title>
				
					<para>
						Use persistent connections when connecting to a database. This is a performance enchanting feature 
						which if enabled will make your forum somewhat faster. Improvment is the result of PHP not needing
						to open a new database connection each time a script is executed, but rather use an existing
						connection instead.
					</para>
					
					<para>
						This option does have it's drawbacks, on forked webservers such as Apache, every Apache child 
						will create a persistent socket for itself. This can potentially exhaust number of allowed database 
						connections if the number of Apache children with open connections to database exceed the allowed number
						of database connections, thus preventing threads without an open connection to connect to the database
						server.
					</para>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>	
			
			<sect3 id="global.pm.options">
				<title>Private Messaging</title>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.PM_ENABLED">
					<title>Allow Private Messaging</title>
				
					<para>
						Whether or not forum members can send private messages to one another.
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.PRIVATE_ATTACHMENTS">
					<title>File Attachments in Private Messages</title>
				
					<para>
						How many file attachments a user can attach to each private message. Setting this option to 0, will
						disable file attachments for private messages.
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.PRIVATE_ATTACH_SIZE">
					<title>Maximum Attachment Size</title>
				
					<para>
						The maximum size, in bytes, of the file(s) a user can attach to their private messages.
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.PRIVATE_MSG_SMILEY">
					<title>Allow Smilies</title>
				
					<para>
						Whether or not smilies/emoticons in private messages will be converted to their graphical equivalents.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.PRIVATE_IMAGES">
					<title>Allow Images</title>
				
					<para>
						This option allows you to limit how many images can users include inside their private messages.
						<note>
							<simpara>
							This limit will only work if the tag style is FUDcode, won't work if you allowed 
							your visitors to use HTML.
							</simpara>
						</note>
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.PRIVATE_TAGS">
					<title>Tag Style</title>
				
					<para>
						What kind of text formatting options are available to the user.
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">FUDcode</emphasis> Users can use <link linkend="fudcode">FUDcode</link> styling tags to format their messages.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">HTML</emphasis> The users can use HTML inside their messages.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">NONE</emphasis> only plain text is allowed.</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.MAX_PMSG_FLDR_SIZE">
					<title>Maximum Private Messages Folder Size</title>
				
					<para>
						The maximum amount of data, in bytes, the users can store inside their private message folders. This
						does not include the space taken up by the file attachments attached to private messages.
					</para>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="global.cookie.options">
				<title>Cookie &amp; Session Settings</title>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.COOKIE_PATH">
					<title>Cookie Path</title>
				
					<para>
						The path of cookie used by the forum. Outside of this path the cookie will not be accessible.
					</para>
				
					<para>
						By default the cookie path is the path to the forum. For example, if your forum URL is 
						"http://mydomain.com/forum/" the cookie path will be "/forum/". If you wanted your entire
						site to be able to access the forum's cookies, change the value of this option to "/".
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.COOKIE_DOMAIN">
					<title>Cookie Domain</title>
				
					<para>
						The domain name for which a cookie is being set, the domain MUST be the same as the one used to access
						the forum, as specified in the <link linkend="global.option.WWW_ROOT">WWW_ROOT</link> option.
					</para>
					
					<important>
						<simpara>
						For browser compatibility this values MUST have no less the two '.' in it.
						</simpara>
					</important>
					
					&user.note;
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.COOKIE_NAME">
					<title>Cookie Name</title>
				
					<para>
						The name of the cookie that will be used by the forum. By default a random value is picked for
						this option to prevent conflicts with any other cookies you may already have. In the very unlikely event 
						that you already have a cookie with such a name, change the value of this option to something else.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.COOKIE_TIMEOUT">
					<title>Cookie Timeout</title>
				
					<para>
						This is the period of time, in seconds after which the browser will remove the cookie. The user who's
						cookie expired will then need to re-login in to the forum.
					</para>
				
					<para>
						By default the cookies are set to expire 7 days they are set. Each time the user 
						access the forum the cookie is renewed for another 7 days.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.SESSION_TIMEOUT">
					<title>Session Timeout</title>
				
					<para>
						If cookies are not used  or are not available sessions will be used instead. They work by passing 
						the information normally stores in a cookie via GET/POST across the forum. Each time a user access' 
						a page their session gets renewed. 
					</para>
					
					<para>
						This option defines the amount of time, in seconds after which the session expires 
						and a user will be required to re-login. For security reasons do not set this to a high number.
					</para>
					
					<para>
						By default, sessions will expire after 30 minutes.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="global.custom.avatar.options">
				<title>Custom Avatar Settings</title>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.CUSTOM_AVATAR_APPOVAL">
					<title>Avatar Approval</title>
				
					<para>
						This toggle defines whether or not the administrator(s) need to approve all the URL &amp; Uploaded avatars
						before they are activated.
					</para>
					
					<tip>
						<simpara>
						Leave this option set to YES, unless you have absolute faith in your users and are certain they will follow
						the size limitations you've defined.	
						</simpara>
					</tip>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.CUSTOM_AVATARS">
					<title>Custom Avatars</title>
				
					<para>
						&FUDforum; allows for a number of ways that a user can specify their avatar, if avatars are allowed.
						This option allows you to define is avatars are allowed and if so, what type of avatars the users may use.	
					</para>
				
					<para>
						The URL &amp; Uploaded avatars will first need to be approved by the admin before they are activated, unless
						you specified in the <link linkend="global.option.CUSTOM_AVATAR_APPOVAL">Avatar Approval</link> option,
						that the admin does not need to approve those avatars.
					</para>
				
					<para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">URL</emphasis> The user can specify their avatar by entering a URL of an image.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Uploaded</emphasis> The user can upload an image from their hard drive to be their avatar.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Built In</emphasis> The user choose an avatar from the ones available in the forum's avatar gallery. <note><simpara>You can add avatars into the avatar gallery via the <link linkend="admin.avatar">Avatar Manager</link> control panel.</simpara></note></para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">ALL</emphasis> The user can specify their avatar by specifying a URL to an image, uploading one to the server or choosing from the forum avatar galleries.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">OFF</emphasis> The avatars are disabled.</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
						
						<note>
							<simpara>
							The actual control panel will have additional values allowing you choose a combination of any of the first three options.
							</simpara>
						</note>
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.CUSTOM_AVATAR_MAX_SIZE">
					<title>Maximum Size of Custom Avatars</title>
				
					<para>
						This is a limit, in bytes, on how big of an image a user can upload as their avatar.
					</para>
				</sect4>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.CUSTOM_AVATAR_MAX_DIM">
					<title>Maximum Dimensions of the Avatar Image</title>
				
					<para>
						This the maximum width x height dimensions of the avatar the user can specify.
					
						<tip>
							<simpara>
							The uploaded avatars can be scaled down by the admin during the avatar approval process
							if the path to <link linkend="global.option.MOGRIFY_BIN">Mogrify</link> utility is specified.
							</simpara>
						</tip>
					</para>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="global.sig.options">
				<title>Signature Settings</title>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.ALLOW_SIGS">
					<title>Allow Signatures</title>
				
					<para>
						Whether or not forum users can specify signatures that will be appended to their messages.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.FORUM_CODE_SIG">
					<title>Tag Style</title>
				
					<para>
						What kind of text formatting options are available to the user.
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">FUDcode</emphasis> Users can use <link linkend="fudcode">FUDcode</link> styling tags to format their messages.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">HTML</emphasis> The users can use HTML inside their messages.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">NONE</emphasis> only plain text is allowed.</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.FORUM_SML_SIG">
					<title>Allow Smilies</title>
				
					<para>
						Whether or not smilies/emoticons in signatures will be converted to their graphical equivalents.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.FORUM_IMG_SIG">
					<title>Allow Images</title>
				
					<para>
						Whether or not images are allowed in signatures.		
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.FORUM_IMG_CNT_SIG">
					<title>Maximum Number of Images</title>
				
					<para>
						This option allows you to limit how many images can users include inside their signatures.
						<note>
							<simpara>
							This limit will only work if the tag style is FUDcode, won't work if you allowed 
							your visitors to use HTML.
							</simpara>
						</note>
					</para>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>	
			
			<sect3 id="global.spell.options">
				<title>Spell Checker</title>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.SPELL_CHECK_ENABLED">
				<para>
					Whether or not the spell checker is enabled.
					
					<note>
						<simpara>
						This option will only work if your PHP has the pspell module enabled.
						</simpara>
					</note>	
				</para>	
				</sect4>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="global.gen.options">
				<title>General Settings</title>
			
				<sect4 id="global.option.MAX_SMILIES_SHOWN">
					<title>Maximum Smilies Shown</title>
				
					<para>
						The maximum number of smilies/emoticons to show shortcuts for on the message posting forms.
						To see the rest the user will need to click on the "list all smilies" link.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.PUBLIC_RESOLVE_HOST">
					<title>Public Host Resolving</title>
				
					<para>
						Toggle the showing of the partially resolved host name of the message's author to other users.
						For example: <screen>me.myself.com will appear as .myself.com</screen>
					</para>
					
					<para>
						This may slow down the posting process, especially, if the user's host mask takes a while to
						resolve.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.MAX_LOGIN_SHOW">
					<title>Maximum Shown Login Length</title>
				
					<para>
						The maximum number of characters of a user's login name to show on all pages with the exception 
						of user info page.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.MAX_LOCATION_SHOW">
					<title>Maximum Shown Location Length</title>
				
					<para>
						The maximum number of characters of a user's location to show on all pages with the 
						exception of user info page.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.LOGEDIN_LIST">
					<title>Logged In Users List Enabled</title>
				
					<para>
						Whether or not the list of currently logged in users is displayed. By default 
						this list is shown on the forum's front page.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.LOGEDIN_TIMEOUT">
					<title>Logged In Users List Timeout</title>
				
					<para>
						The amount of time, in minutes, after which a user is considered to be no longer logged in.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.ACTION_LIST_ENABLED">
					<title>Allow Action List</title>
				
					<para>
						If enabled it allows other forum users to see what their counterparts are doing on the forum
						at the time.
					</para>
					
					<important>
						<simpara>
						This option requires that the <link linkend="global.option.LOGEDIN_LIST">Logged in List</link> be enabled.
						</simpara>
					</important>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.ONLINE_OFFLINE_STATUS">
					<title>Online/Offline Status Indicator</title>
				
					<para>
						If enabled, this option will indicate whether a user is online or offline beside all their message.	
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.ADMIN_EMAIL">
					<title>Administrator E-Mail</title>
				
					<para>
						The e-mail address of the administrator.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.NOTIFY_FROM">
					<title>Notify From</title>
				
					<para>
						All of the system e-mails sent from the forum, such as e-mail post notification, registration 
						confirmation etc... will come from this address.
					</para>
				</sect4>

				<sect4 id="global.option.NOTIFY_WITH_BODY">
					<title>Notify W/Body</title>
				
					<para>
						If enabled, then e-mail notifications will include the complete HTML body of
						the message, allowing the user to read the message's text via their e-mail client
						as well as reply to the message by clicking on the reply/quote buttons.
					</para>
					
					<para>
						In the event the user's e-mail client does not support HTML, the e-mail contains
						a text version of the message as well. 
					</para>
				</sect4>

				<sect4 id="global.option.COPPA">
					<title>COPPA</title>

					<para>
						If enabled the users, will be required to indicate whether or not they are older then 13 years
						of age before registration. If they are not, then their legal guardians will be required to confirm the 
						the account via Fax or E-mail.
					</para>
					
					<para>
						All US based sites must leave this option enabled to comply with the 
						Children's Online Privacy Protection Act of 1998 (COPPA)
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.POSTS_PER_PAGE">
					<title>Posts Per Page</title>
				
					<para>
						How many messages to display per page.				
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.THREADS_PER_PAGE">
					<title>Threads Per Page</title>
				
					<para>
						Indicates how many threads to show per page.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.DEFAULT_THREAD_VIEW">
					<title>Default Thread View</title>
				
					<para>
						Allows the admin to specify the default message view.
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Flat View</emphasis> Standard bulletin board view.</para></listitem>
							<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Tree View</emphasis> Draws a tree like view of the messages. Similar to how messages in the newsgroups are displayed.</para></listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.WORD_WRAP">
					<title>Word Wrap</title>
				
					<para>
						This setting defines on how many characters to wrap message bodies on, any text string longer the the number
						of characters specified in this option will be broken down into 1 or more strings using a space as a separator.
					</para>
					
					<para>	
						Set this to 0 to disable word wrapping.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.UNCONF_USER_EXPIRY">
					<title>Unconfirmed User Expiry</title>
				
					<para>
						The number of days unconfirmed forum members are held in the database.
						They will be removed from database after this period of time.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.FLOOD_CHECK_TIME">
					<title>Flood Trigger</title>
				
					<para>
						The minimum time delay, in seconds between message posting. This option is used to prevent
						automated posting scripts that would attempt to post many messages at once.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.MOVED_THR_PTR_EXPIRY">
					<title>Moved Thread Pointer Expiry</title>
				
					<para>
						The number of days to show a pointer of a moved thread from the original forum to the new forum.
						The pointer will be removed after this period of time.	
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.ALLOW_EMAIL">
					<title>Allow E-mail</title>
				
					<para>
						Allow the users to send e-mails to other forum members using the forum's internal e-mail client.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.SERVER_TZ">
					<title>Server Time Zone</title>
				
					<para>
						Server time zone.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.FORUM_SEARCH">
					<title>Forum Search Engine</title>
				
					<para>
						If enabled the users will be able to do full text searches on the content of the posted messages.
						If you wish to increase the speed of the posting process or save on space used by MySQL you should
						turn this option off.
					</para>
					
					<para>
						In the event Forum Search is disabled the search index will not be populated at the time of posting.
						If you later on decide to enable the search engine you will need to <link linkend="admin.rebuild_search_index">Rebuild Search Index</link>.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.MEMBER_SEARCH_ENABLED">
					<title>Member Search</title>
				
					<para>
						If enabled it will allow forum visitors to search for registered forum users by login and/or email.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.MEMBERS_PER_PAGE">
					<title>Members Per Page</title>
				
					<para>
						How many forum members to display per page on the members list page.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.ANON_NICK">
					<title>Anonymous Username</title>
				
					<para>
						The name that will be used to refer to all unregistered forum users.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.THREAD_MSG_PAGER">
					<title>Quick Pager Link Count</title>
				
					<para>
						How many page links to display beside a thread that exceeds 1 page in length 
						as defined by the <link linkend="global.option.THREADS_PER_PAGE">THREADS_PER_PAGE</link> option.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.GENERAL_PAGER_COUNT">
					<title>General Pager Link Count</title>
				
					<para>
						This is the number of direct links to pages that will be shown in the pager, excluding &lt;&lt; &lt; &gt; &gt;&gt;.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.SHOW_EDITED_BY">
					<title>Show Edited By</title>
				
					<para>
						If enabled then all the messages that were later edited by the author of the message will have
						an indicator showing that the message was edited by it's author.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.EDITED_BY_MOD">
					<title>Show Edited By Moderator</title>
				
					<para>
						If enabled then messages edited by the moderator or the administrator will have an indicator
						indicating showing that the message was edited by someone other then the message author.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.EDIT_TIME_LIMIT">
					<title>Edit Time Limit</title>
				
					<para>
						The time limit, in minutes, past which the users will no longer be able to edit their own messages.
					</para>
					
					<para>
						Set the value to 0 to give unlimited editing time.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.DISPLAY_IP">
					<title>Display IP Publicly</title>
				
					<para>
						Whether or not to display the IP address of the message's author for all forum users.
					</para>
					
					<note>
						<simpara>
						All forum administrators and moderators will be able to see the IP of the message author
						regardless of this option.
						</simpara>
					</note>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.MAX_IMAGE_COUNT">
					<title>Max Image Count</title>
				
					<para>
						The maximum number of images a user may include in their forum messages.
					</para>
					
					<note>
						<simpara>
						This limit will ONLY work if the &fudcode; style is being used.
						</simpara>
					</note>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.SHOW_N_MODS">
					<title># Of Moderators To Show</title>
				
					<para>
						An indicator of how many forum moderators to show beside each forum on the front page.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.EMAIL_CONFIRMATION">
					<title>E-mail Confirmation</title>
				
					<para>
						If enabled each new registration will need to be confirmed via email. A special URL will be sent
						to the e-mail specified by the user during registration, which once accessed will activate their account.
					</para>
					
					<para>
						Unconfirmed accounts will be removed after a set amount of days as defined by the 
						<link linkend="global.option.UNCONF_USER_EXPIRY">UNCONF_USER_EXPIRY</link> option.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.PUBLIC_STATS">
					<title>Public Stats</title>
				
					<para>
						If enabled, at the bottom of each page forum users will be able to see how long it took to generate 
						the page as well as how many MySQL queries were ran and their timings.
					</para>
				</sect4>
				
				<sect4 id="global.option.FORUM_INFO">
					<title>Forum Info</title>
				
					<para>
						If enabled forum statistics will be displayed on the front page. These include 
						total number of approved posts, number of topics and registered users and the last registered user
					</para>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.replacement_censorship_system">
		<title>Replacement &amp; Censorship System</title>
		
		<para>
			The Replacement &amp; Censorship System allows the admin to replace certain strings 
			in the messages, signatures and biographies of the users with another text string.
		</para>	
		
		<para>
			The most common use of this system is to censor certain words and phrases that the
			admin feels are in appropriate for the forum. For this purpose &FUDforum; offers two syntaxes
			for replacing text ranging from a simple replace to a complex regular expression.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.replacement_censorship_system.str_replace">
			<title>String Replace</title>
			
			<para>
				The most basic and the easiest to use string replacement option is "String Replace". This option will
				allow you to specify the 'Replace' string with its alternative the 'With' string.
				For example, if you specify the replace string as "haystack" and it's alternative as needle then
				<screen>this haystack is sharp.</screen>
				will be converted to:
				<screen>this needle is sharp.</screen>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.replacement_censorship_system.ereg_replace">
			<title>Perl Regex</title>
			
			<para>
				Perl Regex will use a perl regular expression library to perform a replacement on a text or a text mask.
				This although slower then str_replace it allows for a much more powerful and sophisticated text manipulation.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					This functionality uses PHP's PECL library and utilize the preg_replace function. PHP's documentation
					of this function and its capabilities &amp; syntax can be found 
					<ulink url="http://www.php.net/manual/en/function.preg-replace.php"><citetitle>here</citetitle></ulink>.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Lets say, you want to replace all words containing the string 'spoon' with 'fork'.
				Clearly you cannot use <link linkend="admin.replacement_censorship_system.str_replace">String Replace</link> 
				for this because it would not replace the entire word but only the 'spoon' part. 
				For this purpose you need to use the power of regular expressions.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Inside the 'Replace' field we enter the <screen>!(\s|^)([^\s]*?)spoon([^\s]*?)(\s|$)!i</screen> regular expression and
				enter <screen>\1fork\4</screen> as the 'With' alternative. The end result of this regex that any word containing 
				the string 'spoon' will be replaced with "fork". Because we've added the 'i' parameter to our regex, which 
				made it case-insensitive, so even the "SpOon" instances will be found and replaced.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Because the regular expression is generally rather complex there is no easy way &FUDforum; can figure out how to
				reverse it back, so that when the person is editing their text they can see the text that they have originally entered.
				Therefor you get 2 extra fields ('From post' and 'To')were you get to specify the "reverse" regex that would 
				convert the replaced data back its original form. Based on the previous example involving "fork" &amp; "spoon" the 
				conversion back strings would look like this: 
<screen>
From post:	!(\s|^)fork(\s|$)!
To:		spoon
</screen>	
			</para>
			
			
		</sect2>
		
		<note>
			<simpara>
			The messages &amp; signatures entered prior the the addition of a replace will not be affected by the newly added replace syntax.
			</simpara>
		</note>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.mime_managment_system">
		<title>MIME Managment System</title>
		
		<para>
			This control panel allows you to manage mime types &amp; icons for the various files
			that the forum users can attach to their messages.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			MIME types are special strings sent to the browser that tell the browser how to interpret the file.
			For example .exe file would have a application/application MIME type, which would tell the browser that the file
			should be saved to the user's hard rive instead of trying to open the file. On the other hand for .jpg image 
			the forum would send a image/jpeg MIME, which would tell the browser to display the image in the browser window.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The MIME types are determined by the file extension and compared to the extensions of the supported MIME types inside
			the &FUDforum; database. If the file does not match any MIME types it would be assigned the generic application/ocet-stream
			MIME type, which would tell the browser to save the file rather then try to display it.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The forum by default comes with 30 or so default MIME types that cover the most commonly used file types, so unless
			you have special file types not covered by this list you will not need to use this control panel.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Adding of a new MIME is normally a 2 step process, first you upload the image that you want to represent 
			your new MIME and then you enter the actual MIME information such as a description, file extension and mime header.
			The 1st step can be bypassed if you already have an image that you wish to use in association with this MIME
			by choosing the image from the list of the ones already available in the forum.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="mime.uploading">
			<title>Uploading MIME image</title>
				
			<para>
				At the top of the MIME managment form there is a simple control, which allows you to choose an image 
				from your drive and upload it to the server. Clicking on a browse link will open up a dialog allowing you
				to pick the image.
			</para>
				
			<para>
				Click on the upload link to upload the image to the forum.
			</para>
				
			<para>
				The preview of the uploaded image will appear on the MIME Managment control and the file name 
				will automatically be inserted into the <link linkend="mime.icon">MIME Icon</link> textbox.
			</para>
		</sect2>
			
		<sect2 id="mime.info">
			<title>Editing/Adding MIME Information</title>
				
			<para>
				Now that you've uploaded your MIME image you can now specify the MIME information. If you choose to use
				an existing image, by clicking on the "select MIME icon" link that would pull up a pop-up window where all the 
				MIME images in the system will be displayed and you'll be able to choose the one you want by clicking on it.
			</para>
				
			<para>
				If you are editing a MIME, the information for the MIME will be automatically inserted in to the appropriate
				fields so you can easily edit it.
			</para>
				
			<sect3 id="mime.descr">
				<title>MIME Description</title>
				
				<para>
					Use this field to enter a quick description of the MIME. This field's data will not show up anywhere
					on the forum other then this form.
				</para>
			</sect3>
				
			<sect3 id="mime.header">
				<title>MIME Header</title>
					
				<para>
					This is the MIME header that will be sent to the browser when the user downloads a file that 
					matches this MIME type.
				</para>
			</sect3>
				
			<sect3 id="mime.ext">
				<title>File Extension</title>
					
				<para>
					Files that end with this extension will be attributed assigned mime type.
				</para>
					
				<para>
					This value is case-insensitive, so jpg and JPG are the same thing as far as MIME management system
					is concerned.
				</para>
			</sect3>
				
			<sect3 id="mime.icon">
				<title>MIME Icon</title>
					
				<para>
					This is an image that will be displayed beside all file attachments that are of this MIME type.
				</para>
			</sect3>
				
			<sect3 id="mime.icon.preview">
				<title>Preview Image</title>
					
				<para>
					This field uses JavaScript to give you a preview of the currently selected MIME Icon.
				</para>
			</sect3>
				
			<para>
				Once all the MIME information is set to your satisfaction click on the "Add MIME" or the "Update" button, 
				depending of whether you're adding or updating a MIME, to submit your changes.
			</para>
		</sect2>
			
		<sect2 id="mime.list">
			<title>MIME List</title>
				
			<para>
				At the bottom of the MIME Manager there is a list of all the MIME types supported by the forum.
				Beside each MIME there is an edit link allowing you to edit this MIME as well as a delete link, which will
				delete the MIME.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.file_manager">
		<title>File Manager</title>
		
		<para>
			The file manager is a utility that allows you to easily manage files inside the forum's directories.
			Using this tool you can change file permissions, upload files, delete files as well as download files
			using your web browser.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The file manager displays the file &amp; directory listing akin to the one shown by the *NIX 'ls -lia' command, with
			a slight addition of showing the permission's integer value.
			<example>
				<title>File List Example</title>
<screen>
Mode			Owner	Group	Size	Date	Time		Name		Action
-rwxrwxrwx- (777)	forum	forum	0 KB	Mar 13	18:28:03	blank.gif   	chmod  | download | delete
</screen>			
			</example>
		</para>
		
		<note>
			<simpara>
			This utility is only for *NIX installations, it is not available for Windows installations of the forum.
			</simpara>
		</note>
		
		<sect2 id="file_manager.mkdir">
			<title>Making Directories</title>
			
			<para>
				The file manager allows you to create directories. Simply enter the directory in the 'Directory Name' textbox and
				and click on the 'Create Directory' link. This will create a directory with the name you've specified inside 
				current directory.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="file_manager.file_upload">
			<title>Uploading Files</title>
			
			<para>
				You can also use the file manager to upload files from your computer into the forum.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				In the File Upload control use the 'browse' button to select the file from your hard drive. If you want 
				to give name other the the original name to the file you are about to be upload, enter the new name inside the
				'File Name' textbox. Now, click on the 'Upload File' button to upload the file into the directory you are currently
				in. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="file_manager.delete">
			<title>Deleting Files &amp; Directories</title>
			
			<para>
				The file manager can also be used to remove forum files &amp; directories. This can be accomplished by clicking on
				the delete link beside each file or directory.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					Directory MUST be empty before it can be deleted.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
			
			<para>
				For safety there is an intermediate stage in the deletion process that will ask you to confirm the fact that you want
				to delete a file or directory. This is done to prevent accidental file deletion.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="file_manager.download">
			<title>Downloading Files</title>
			
			<para>
				Beside each file there is download link, if clicked it would allow you to download the file to your hard drive.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="file_manager.chmod">
			<title>Changing File Permissions</title>
			
			<para>
				The primary feature of the file manager is the ability to change permissions on the forum's files and directories.
				This can be accomplished by clicking on the 'chmod' link, which will pop-up a windows where the files and/or 
				directory permissions can be changed.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.file_lock">
		<title>Lock/Unlock Forum's Files</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; is designed with a security minded approach to data storage. This means that &FUDforum; tries to
			ensure that your forum's data is as secure as possible. Therefor the forum's files are kept with the most
			minimalistic permissions (0600 for files and 0700 for directories), allowing only the web server to access
			those files. Thus they can be altered only using the forum's control panel, preventing other users from
			seeing and modifying your files.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			There may be situations where you would need the ability to access many or all of the forum's files
			right away and changing permissions of each file using the file manager would be excessively difficult.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			This control panel allows the administrator to 'unlock' the forum's files hence allowing those files to be 
			accessed via FTP and SSH/Telnet. Once your are done, is is HIGHLY recommended that your 'lock' the forum back
			hence re-instating the secure permissions on your data.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			This form can work virtually independently of the forum, so to 'lock' or 'unlock' files the administrator
			would need to specify their login &amp; password and click on the appropriate button depending on which
			action they wish to perform.
		</para>
		
		<note>
			<simpara>
			This utility is only for *NIX installation, it is not available for Windows installations of the forum.
			</simpara>
		</note>
	</sect1>	                
	
	<sect1 id="admin.forum_statistics">
		<title>Forum Statistics</title>
		
		<para>
			This utility allows you to gather statistics about your forum's usage. In addition to forum statistics this
			utility will also show you a detailed breakdown of the hard drive space used by the forum as well as the amount of
			MySQL disk space used by the forum.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The statistics engine can be used to analyze the following information:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Number of Posted Message</emphasis> The number of posted within a defined time frame.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Number of Threads</emphasis> The number of threads within a defined time frame.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Registered Users</emphasis> The number of new user registrations within a defined time frame.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>	
			
			You can also specify the detail of the information, by specifying the level of detail, such as daily, weekly, monthly or yearly.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.action_log_viewer">
		<title>Action Log Viewer</title>
		
		<para>
			All administrative actions of privileged users are logged by &FUDforum; so that they can later be reviewed by the admin.
		</para>
		
		<para>	
			This control panel allows the admin to see this information by displaying the user name, action, the affected forum data
			as well as the time of the event.
		</para>
		
		<tip>
			<simpara>	
			In addition to logging actions of privileged users this control panel also allows the admin to see failed logins attempts 
			into any of the accounts that have administrative access to the forum, with the IP address of the user who attempted to login. This is 
			an extremely useful feature for tracking down attempted hacking attempts, by people who try to gain administrative access
			by guessing the password of the administrator(s).
			</simpara>
		</tip>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.system_info">
		<title>System Info</title>
		
		<para>
			Provides various details about the server setup of the machine &FUDforum; is running on.
		</para>
		
		<important>
			<simpara>
			When reporting a bug with a forum, please include the output of this control panel.
			</simpara>
		</important>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.category_forum_management">
		<title>Category &amp; Forum Management</title>
		
		<para>
			The Category &amp; Forum Management control panel allows the administrator to manage the forum's categories and forums.
			This is a 2 stage control panel, first stage involves the category managment and the 2nd deals with the forums inside
			a particular category.	
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.category_forum_management.cat">
			<title>Category Managment</title>
			
			<para>
				The first control panel you see when you click on the 'Category &amp; Forum Management' link is the category manager.
				This control panel allows you to create/edit/remove and reposition the categories of your forum.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				At the top of the page there is a form that would allow you to add a new category. When you are editing 
				a category the form's values will be filled up with the category's properties allowing you to edit them.
			</para>
			
			<sect3 id="cat.name">
				<title>Category Name</title>
				
				<para>
					The name of the category.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="cat.descr">
				<title>Description</title>
				
				<para>
					Description of the category, this text will appear adjacent to the category name.
					
					<note><simpara>You can put raw HTML into this field.</simpara></note>
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="cat.collapse">
				<title>Collapsible</title>
				
				<para>
					Whether or not the users can collapse this category on the front page.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="cat.def">
				<title>Default view</title>
				
				<para>
					Whether or not this category will appear collapsed or uncollapsed by default on the front page.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="cat.pos">
				<title>Insert position</title>
				
				<para>
					Where to insert the category, below or on top of all the other categories in the forum.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<para>
				Below the form there is a list of all the existing categories in the forum. This list contains links that allow 
				you to 
				<link linkend="cat.edit_forum">edit the category</link>, 
				<link linkend="cat.delete">delete a category</link>, 
				<link linkend="cat.cpos">change its position in the category list</link> and 
				<link linkend="cat.edit_forum">edit the forums inside this category</link>.
			</para>
			
			<sect3 id="cat.edit_forum">
				<title>Edit Forums</title>
				
				<para>
					When you click on this link you will be taken to a <link linkend="admin.category_forum_management.forum">forum managment page</link>, 
					allowing you to manage the forums assigned to this category.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="cat.edit">
				<title>Edit Category</title>
				
				<para>
					Edit the category options &amp; properties.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="cat.delete">
				<title>Delete</title>
				
				<para>
					Clicking this link will delete the category and all of the forums assigned to it.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="cat.cpos">
				<title>Change Position</title>
				
				<para>
					Clicking on the change link will allow you to change the order in which this category is displayed on 
					the forum's pages. 
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.category_forum_management.forum">
			<title>Forum Managment</title>
			
			<para>
				The forum manager allows the administrator to manage forums that are assigned to a particular category. This includes
				adding/removing controls, ability to move a forum to a different category as well as change display order of the forum.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				The first item on the forum manager page is form that allows the admin to add and edit forums. When a forum is
				being edited the forum's settings will be pulled into the form for ease of editing.
			</para>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.name">
				<title>Forum Name</title>
				
				<para>
					The name of the forum.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.descr">
				<title>Description</title>
				
				<para>
					Forum's description, this text will be shown right below the forum name.
					
					<note>
						<simpara>
						Can contain raw HTML.
						</simpara>
					</note>
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.tag">
				<title>Tag Style</title>
				
				<para>
					What kind of text formatting tools are available to the user.
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">FUDcode</emphasis> Users can use <link linkend="fudcode">FUDcode</link> styling tags to format their messages.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">HTML</emphasis> The users can use HTML inside their messages.</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">NONE</emphasis> only plain text is allowed.</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>			
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.pp">
				<title>Password Posting</title>
				
				<para>
					Whether or users will be required to enter a special password in order to be able to post messages inside
					this forum.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.password">
				<title>Posting Password</title>
				
				<para>
					If you've specified that users must enter a password in order to post messages, you should enter the password
					inside this field.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.mod">
				<title>Moderated Forum</title>
				
				<para>
					If set to yes, any new message will need to be approved by the forum's moderator or an administrator before it
					becomes visible to the public.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.filesize">
				<title>Max Attachment Size</title>
				
				<para>
					The maximum size, in kilobytes of the attached files users can attach to their messages.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.max_files">
				<title>Change Position</title>
				
				<para>
					The maximum number of files users can attach to their messages.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.msg_threshold">
				<title>Message Threshold</title>
				
				<para>
					Only the number of bytes of the messages inside this forum will be shown. For example, if you set this 
					limit to 1000 bytes and a user entered a 1500 byte long message only the 1st 1000 bytes of the message
					will be shown. To see the rest the message user will need to click on the 'Show the rest of the message' link.
				</para>
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					Setting this option to 0 means that unlimited message length is allowed, effectively disabling this feature.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.icon">
				<title>Forum Icon</title>
				
				<para>
					You can choose to have an icon displayed beside the forum. By clicking on the 'SELECT ICON' link you will 
					be able to choose an icon for your forum.
				</para>
				
				<para>
					You can upload additional forum icons in addition to the one installed by default via the 
					<link linkend="admin.forum_icons">Forum Icon Manager</link>.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.pos">
				<title>Insert position</title>
				
				<para>
					Where to insert the forum, below or on top of all the other forums in the category.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<para>
				Below the forum editor there a list of all the forums inside the category you are editing. Using this
				listing you can edit, delete, move to another category or change the position of the forum inside
				the current category.
			</para>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.edit">
				<title>Edit</title>
				
				<para>
					Edit the forum options &amp; properties.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.delete">
				<title>Delete</title>
				
				<para>
					Clicking this link will delete the forum.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.move">
				<title>Move</title>
				
				<para>
					This option allows the administrator to move a forum from its current category to a different
					category.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			
			<sect3 id="forum.cpos">
				<title>Change Position</title>
				
				<para>
					Clicking on the change link will allow you to change the position of forum on the page. For example 
					move the 4th forum inside the category to the 2nd position.
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.deleted.forums">
		<title>Deleted Forums</title>
		
		<para>
			When a forum is deleted it is not immediately removed from the database but rather moved to a trash bin of sorts.
			It is done to allow the admin to restore the accidentally removed forums, since once they are truly removed 
			there is no going back.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			This control panel allows the admin to see all the forums inside the 'trash bin' and allows the admin to either
			restore the forum, by choosing a category where to restore the forum by clicking on the 'Reassign' button
			or to truly delete the forum by clicking on the delete link.
		</para>
		
		<tip>
			<simpara>
			It is a good idea to run the <link linkend="admin.compact_messages">Compact Messages</link> utility 
			after deletion of a forum, especially if that forum had many messages in it.
			</simpara>
		</tip>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.announce.manager">
		<title>Announcement Manager</title>
		
		<para>
			Announcement manager control panel that allows the administrator to create global announcements that would appear
			in selected forums at the top of the thread listing.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="ann.forums">
			<title>Forums</title>
			
			<para>
				This option allows the administrator to define in which forums the announcement will appear, by selecting
				the checkbox beside the each forum. There is also a convenient 'All' button for selecting all of the 
				forums at once, as well as a 'None' button to unselect all of the selected forums.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="ann.st_date">
			<title>Starting Date</title>
			
			<para>
				This option specifies from which date the announcement will be visible.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="ann.en_date">
			<title>Ending Date</title>
			
			<para>
				The announcement will not be shown past this date.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="ann.subject">
			<title>Subject</title>
			
			<para>
				The subject of the announcement.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="ann.message">
			<title>Message</title>
			
			<para>
				This this the actual content of the announcement, you can put raw HTML into this textarea.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<para>
			Below the announcement creation/editor form there is a list of all the current announcements in the system.
			Beside each announcement there is a link allowing the administrator to edit or delete the announcement.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.thread.prunning">
		<title>Thread Prunning</title>
		
		<para>
			The thread prunning control panel allows the admin to remove threads that are older then a certain date.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="thread.prunning.period">
			<title>Time Period</title>
			
			<para>
				Whether the indicated 'age' is a number of days, weeks, months or years.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="thread.prunning.num">
			<title>Numeric Value</title>
			
			<para>
				Threads that are older then this number of days, weeks, months or years as specified by the 'Time Period'
				option, will be pruned.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="thread.prunning.frm">
			<title>Forum Limiter</title>
			
			<para>
				Allows the admin to specify a specific forum or category which to prune or whether to prune all forums.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<para>
			Once you click on the prune button the forum will calculate the number of threads that will be affected by the 
			prunning and ask you to confirm that you indeed wish to prune that number of threads. If you confirm the process
			the affected threads will be removed.
		</para>
		
		<tip>
			<simpara>
			It is a good idea to run the <link linkend="admin.compact_messages">Compact Messages</link> utility 
			after doing thread prunning.
			</simpara>
		</tip>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.user_manager">
		<title>Moderator/User Manager</title>
		
		<para>
			This control allows the administrator to manage users as well as assign and/or remove moderation
			permission from users.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.find">
			<title>Choosing a User</title>
			
			<para>
				The first step of managing a user is picking a user which you want to edit. You can do so
				by entering the login name or the email address of the use into the appropriate fields on the 
				user manager control panel.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				The control panel allows for partial matching, so you can enter masks such as 'ad*', which would
				find all users who's login name begins with an 'ad'. 
			</para>
			
			<para>
				If there is only one matching user, their information will be retrieved into the user manager. If more
				then one user matches, then you will be presented with a list of all the matching users and will be able
				to pick the user you want to manage by clicking on their login name.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<para>
			Now that you've pulled up the user information inside the user manager you can proceed to modify the various
			user settings.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.login">
			<title>Change Login Name</title>
			
			<para>
				The user manager allows the administrator to change the login of the user who's account is being edited.
				This can be accomplished by entering a different login into the 'Login' field and clicking on the 
				'Change Login Name' button.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					Make sure the login you're going to enter is not already in use, otherwise the process will fail.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.password">
			<title>Change Password</title>
			
			<para>
				The user manager allows the administrator to change the password of the who's account is being edited.
				To change the password enter a new password into the 'Password' textbox and press the 'Change Password'
				button.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					By default 'Password' textbox will always be empty since passwords are encrypted with a 1 way
					algorithm, MD5 for greater security and cannot be decoded back.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.profile">
			<title>Change User's Profile</title>
			
			<para>
				Clicking on this link will take the administrator to the profile control panel where they can edit
				the user's profile and settings. The administrator will need to enter the their password on that form
				to activate any of the changes that were made.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.admin">
			<title>Forum Administrator</title>
			
			<para>
				This options shows whether this user is an administrator or not. By clicking on the toggle link the 
				administrator can assign or remove administrative privileges from a user.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.blocked">
			<title>Blocked</title>
			
			<para>
				Whether or not this user is blocked from posting messages on the forum.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.coppa">
			<title>COPPA</title>
			
			<para>
				Whether or not this account requires COPPA confirmation.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					If the value is set to 'Y', then this account is pending COPPA confirmation.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Children's Online Privacy Protection Act of 1998 (COPPA) indicates that all accounts of
				children under the age of 13 must be confirmed by their legal guardians via FAX or Snail Mail.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.econf">
			<title>E-mail Confirmation</title>
			
			<para>
				Whether or not this account has been confirmed via e-mail. <link linkend="global.option.EMAIL_CONFIRMATION">If enabled</link> 
				in the admin control panel all new accounts must be confirmed via e-mail before they activated.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.mod">
			<title>Moderating Forums</title>
			
			<para>
				Shows the list of the forum this user is moderating. Clicking on the 'Modify Moderation Permissions' 
				link will open up a pop-up with a list of all the forums. By checking a checkbox beside each forum
				the administrator can assign moderation permissions for that forum to this user. Unchecking a checked
				checkbox will remove moderation permissions from the user.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.ctag">
			<title>Custom Tags</title>
			
			<para>
				The administrator can assign an unlimited number of custom tags to a user. This option allows the admin
				to enter the new custom tags for the user, by entering the text into the 'Custom Tags' textbox and pressing
				the 'Add' button.
				<note>
					<simpara>
					Custom tags may contain raw HTML.
					</simpara>
				</note>
				
				All of the user's current custom tags are listed above the textbox and can be removed by clicking the 
				'Delete' link beside each custom tag.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Custom tags are little bits of text and/or HTML that are displayed on the user's profile page as well
				as inside the author information bit beside all their messages. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<para>
			At the bottom of the user control panel there are a number of links that allow the admin to take certain actions
			in regard to the selected user.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.pm">
			<title>Send Private Message</title>
			
			<para>
				Send a private message to this user using the private messaging system.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					This link will only be available if the 
					<link linkend="global.option.PM_ENABLED">private messaging system is enabled</link>.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.email">
			<title>Send Email</title>
			
			<para>
				Send an e-mail to the user. If the <link linkend="global.option.ALLOW_EMAIL">forum's internal email system is enabled</link> 
				it will be used, otherwise standard mailto: URL will be given, allowing the administrator 
				to send the e-mail using their mail client.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.posts">
			<title>See Posts</title>
			
			<para>
				Clicking this link will show all the posts made by this user.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.rpass">
			<title>Reset Password</title>
			
			<para>
				Resets the user's password and sends the randomly generated password via e-mail to the user.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.user_manager.del">
			<title>Delete User</title>
			
			<para>
				Delete this user account, once deleted there is no way to retrieve the user's account it will be
				permanently lost, be careful when using this option.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.group_control_panel">
		<title>Groups Manager</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; includes a powerful and flexible group managment system. which gives the administrator
			fined grained control over the actions that the users can perform on the forum.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			This control panel allows the administrator to manage the groups, add and remove group leaders as well as
			specify which permissions the group leaders can assign to members of the groups they manage. The control 
			panel allows the administrator to define, which resources (forums) a particular group can control.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			By default &FUDforum; automatically will create a group for every forum that is created. Those groups will carry
			the same name as the forum with the addition of the 'FORUM:' prefix. These groups cannot be deleted manually and
			will automatically be removed when the forum is deleted.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			In addition &FUDforum; also has two global groups, 'Global Anonymous Access' and 'Global Registered Access',
			the group serve a special purpose of defining the default permissions for special 'anonymous' and 'registered' 
			users, who's permissions define the actions those users may perform.
			<example>
				<title>Global Groups</title>
				
				<para>
					Lets say that you do not wish to give the anonymous users the ability to read messages inside
					any new forums you create. You can do this by modifying the permissions for the anonymous user
					in every automatically generated group created for new forum. This is obviously is rather awkward
					and inconvenient especially on large forums.
				</para>
				
				<para>
					In this case using a Global Group can simplify and automate the process. By editing the
					'Global Anonymous Access' group and taking away the 'Visible' &amp; 'Read' permissions you
					ensure that any new auto-generated groups will not allow anonymous users to view the 
					resources (forums) that this group controls. With this single change, you were able to 
					avoid much manual labor of having to change the permissions granted to anonymous users
					in every group, which affects anonymous users.
				</para>
			</example>
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.group_control_panel.res">
			<title>Group Resources</title>
			
			<para>
				Resources describe various things that the group system can control the permissions
				for, currently the group system is only capable of controlling forums, in the future
				its possible that the group system will be tasked with controlling permissions
				for other resources.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				It's possible to have a group control multiple resources
				<caution>
					<simpara>
					It's possible to have resource conflicts, for example
					giving two groups control of the same resource. This 
					isn't a problem for the group system as it will
					try to intelligently resolve the situation,
					see <xref linkend="admin.group_control_panel.conflicts"/>
					</simpara>
				</caution>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.group_control_panel.leader">
			<title>Group Leaders</title>
			
			<para>
				Group Leaders are users who have the ability to add
				other users to groups and control their permissions,
				When adding other users to a group using the group
				manager control form they are able to specify the
				permissions of the user they are adding. However, a
				group leader can never give a user a permission
				for something that he himself is unable to do. 
				
				<caution>
					<simpara>
					It's possible to have group leader conflicts,
					this shouldn't be a problem for the forum as it
					will try to intelligently resolve the situation
					see <xref linkend="admin.group_control_panel.conflicts"/>
					</simpara>
				</caution>
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Beside each group there is a list of permissions, the permissions which are set to 'Yes' can be
				assigned or removed by the group leaders from the users in the group.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				If a particular permission is set to inherit, then this permission will be retrieved from the group
				who's permissions the current group inherits.
				
				<example id="example.permission.inheritance">
					<title>Permission Inheritance</title>
					
					<para>
						Lets suppose there is a group 'Group A', which allows the group manager to control 
						the 'Visible','Read' and 'Post' permissions. There is also  group 'Group B', 
						which inherits 'Visible' and 'Read' permissions from 'Group A'. 
					</para>
					
					<para>
						While the permissions in 'Group A' allow the group manager(s) to control 
						'Visible' and 'Read' permissions same would be true for group manager(s) in the 'Group B'.
						Should the administrator take away the ability to control the 'Read' permission
						from the forum 'Group A' managers, the 'Group B' managers will also loose 
						the ability to change the 'Read' permission from the members of their group.
					</para>
				</example>
				
				The inheritance option is particularly useful if you are creating many similar groups and/or wish to have
				the ability to change the permissions of multiple groups by altering the permissions of a single group.
			</para>
			
			<sect3 id="admin.group_control_panel.manage_leaders">
				<title>Managing Leaders</title>
			
				<para>
					Beside each group there is a 'Manage Leaders' link, which would allow the administrator to
					add and remove group leaders. The list of current group leaders is also listed beside each
					group.
					
					<tip>
						<simpara>
						If you do not know the exact login of the user you wish to make a leader, enter a partial
						login and the list of matches will be presented to you.
						</simpara>
					</tip>
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.group_control_panel.mgr">
			<title>Adding &amp; Editing Groups</title>
			
			<para>
				This form, which is located top of the page allows the administrator to add and edit groups.
			</para>
			
			<sect3 id="admin.group_control_panel.group_name">
				<title>Group Name</title>
				
				<para>
					Group name can be whatever you want, it's preferable you name it something descriptive
					for future reference. It is generally a good idea, to name a group in such a way
					that it is possible to see which resources (forums) are controlled by this group by looking
					at it's name.
				</para>
			</sect3>
		
			<sect3 id="admin.group_control_panel.group_resources">
				<title>Group Resources</title>
				
				<para>
					Controls the resources (forums) that the group permissions will be applied to, it is 
					possible for a group to control multiple resources.
				</para>
			</sect3>
		
			<sect3 id="admin.group_control_panel.inherit_from">
				<title>Inherit From</title>
			
				<para>
					Groups can inherit permissions from other groups, this allows
					you to select from which group, the current group should inherit it's permissions from.
					
					<tip>
						<simpara>
						An example of how permission inheritance works can be found 
						<link linkend="example.permission.inheritance">here</link>.
						</simpara>
					</tip>
				</para>
			</sect3>
		
			<sect3 id="admin.group_control_panel.anon_reg_masks">
				<title>Anonymous and Registered Masks</title>
			
				<para>
					This control whether or not this group will be able to affect the permissions of
					the resources assigned for to this group for all of the anonymous and registered users.
					This is a particularly dangerous option since it can be used to grant or take away permissions
					from a large group of users simultaneously.
				</para>
				
				<para>
					Misuse of this option, can for example block access to all registered users to all of the forums
					controlled by this group if used improperly.
				</para>
			</sect3>
		
			<sect3 id="admin.group_control_panel.permissions">
				<title>Permissions</title>
			
				<para>
					These are the actual permissions of the group, they control the 
					<emphasis role="bold">maximum</emphasis> allowed permissions for the 
					group leaders and regular users belonging to this group.
				</para>
				
				<para>
					Each permission can have 3 values:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>Yes, indicates that the members of this group are allowed perform this action</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>No, indicates that the members of this group are NOT allowed to perform this action</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Inherit, indicates that the group inherits it's permissions from the parent group, as specified in the 'Inherit From' option.</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="admin.group_control_panel.users">
			<title>Adding Users to a Group</title>
			
			<para>
				The administrator can add/remove regular users from a group by clicking on the 'Manage Users' link
				located near each group or by using the 'Group(s) Manager' link on the forum's pages.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.group_control_panel.conflicts">
			<title>Resolving Conflicts</title>
			
			<para>
				The group system allows a creation of conflicts by design, consider
				the following situation
			</para>
			
			<para>
				You created a group named G1 which allows members to READ messages inside forum
				F1, and created a leader U1 in that group.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Now you create a group called G2, which allows members to post messages inside
				forum F1 and made U1 the leader of the group.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Now you have a conflict of permissions, because both G1 and G2 control
				the same resource and have the same user in them, so which permissions
				should the forum give U1? posting or viewing?
			</para>
			
			<para>
				What will happen in reality, is that forum will grant group leader U1 both READ and
				POST permissions to the forum F1 because the logic for the group leaders is additive.
				Which means, that the highest possible permissions will be granted to a group leader.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				This works opposite for normal users, if U1 was a normal user (i.e. NOT a group leader)
				then the logic would have been subtractive, that is, since is the permissions wouldn't 
				have been added. U1 would have ended up without READ and POST permissions.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.mass_email">
		<title>Mass Mail System</title>
		
		<para>
			This control panel allows the administrator to send an e-mail message to all the registered users.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.mass_email.over">
			<title>Ignore User Override</title>
			
			<para>
				The user can specify that they wish to ignore admin's emails via their profile settings. However,
				if the admin feels that the message is important enough that all forum members should receive it, then
				they can overwrite the user's setting, by selecting this option.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.ranks">
		<title>Rank Manager</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; allow the administrator to define user ranks that will be assigned to users once they reach a 
			certain number of posts. This control panel allows the admin to define those ranks.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Each rank is normally a text string, however the admin may choose to have the rank represented by an image
			or a combination of an image and text.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.ranks.name">
			<title>Rank Name</title>
			
			<para>
				This field contains the text that would be displayed beside the names of all the forum users who 
				have attained this rank.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					This field may contain raw HTML.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.ranks.image">
			<title>Rank Image</title>
			
			<para>
				If you wish the rank to be represented by an image enter the name of the image inside this textbox. 
				The images that you wish to use in combination with rank's should be placed inside the forum's
				images directory, which can be found inside <link linkend="global.option.WWW_ROOT">WWW_ROOT</link>.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.ranks.wimage">
			<title>Which Image to Show</title>
			
			<para>
				If you have chosen to have rank represented by an image, you may give this image preference over the user's
				avatar, that way only 1 image is displayed, or vise versa. You may also choose that both the avatar and 
				the rank image will be displayed.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.ranks.pcount">
			<title>Post Count</title>
			
			<para>
				The minimum number of posts the user must make before they achieve this rank.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<para>
			Below the rank editor form, there is a list of all the current ranks in the forum. You may choose to edit or delete
			the ranks by clicking on the appropriate link beside each rank.
		</para>
		
		<important>
			<simpara>
			After making any modifications you MUST run the 'Cache Rebuilder' by clicking on the link at the top of the
			Rank Manager form.
			</simpara>
		</important>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.template_editor">
		<title>Template Editor</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; has a complete templating system that allows the administrator to customize and change the 
			appearance of their forum in it's entirety.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			This control panel offers a web interface to the templates, allowing the admin to change the templates 
			via their browser. This is generally intended for quick changes and/or fixes, if you intend to do a complete
			layout redesign we recommend changing the templates (*.tmpl files inside the template/tmpl/ directory) 
			with your text editor of choice.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The template editor shows the administrator a list of all the available templates that make up the various forum pages. 
			clicking on the red + link beside each template it will expand the template, showing all the sub-templates 
			that make up this page. 
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The primary page template has a light purple color, this template defines how the page and it's elements will
			be constructed. The other sub-templates, which are colored black define the various page elements that make up
			the page. Beside some templates who's name may not explain their purpose you can find green explanation text
			that will tell you the purpose of the template.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			If you click on the template, the template's data will be loaded in to a text area allowing you to edit the
			template. The template's data is mostly comprised of raw HTML with certain template tags representing the dynamic
			data that will be inserted into the template.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The following, are the non HTML template entities that can be found inside the template.
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">{MSG: msg_key}</emphasis> Reference to a message inside the i18n messages file.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">{VAR: var_key}</emphasis> PHP variable</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">{DEF: var_key}</emphasis> PHP define</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">{VAR-HTML: var_key}</emphasis> PHP variable that will be encoded using htmlspecialchars() function</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">{VAR-URL: var_key}</emphasis> PHP variable that will be encoded using urlencode() function</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">{TEMPLATE-DATA: var_key}</emphasis> Template's data which is stored in a variable.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">{TEMPLATE: tmplate_name}</emphasis> Include template with the specified name here</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">{DATE: var_key date_format}</emphasis> Print date based on var_key passing the date_format as the date's format to strftime() function</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">{ALT-VAR: alt_name key1 key2 ...}</emphasis> Color alternator, it will alternate the colors specified as key#</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>	
			
			<note>
				<simpara>
				If you edit the tmpl files manually you will also come across the 
				<emphasis role="bold">{REF: template_file_name}</emphasis> tag. This tag tells the template compiler
				to include the source of the said file when generating the page you are editing. The compiler then will
				inline the file when its generating this page.
				</simpara>
			</note>
		</para>
		
		<para>
			To save your changes, click on the 'Save Changes' button, this will not only save your changes but also 
			recompile the template putting the changes you've made live. So, that you will be able to see how those changes
			altered the layout of the page.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			If you wish edit to content of the text shown on the page, click on the 'Edit Text Messages', which will
			allow you to edit all of the text messages used on this page using the 
			<link linkend="admin.message_editor">Message Editor</link>.
		</para>
		
		<important>
			<simpara>
			After making manual modifications to the template(s), click on the <link linkend="admin.rebuild_templates">Rebuild Templates</link>
			option in the admin control panel to activate the changes you have made.
			</simpara>
		</important>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.message_editor">
		<title>Message Editor</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; included i18n support, which allows the administrator to easily pick a language other then English for 
			their forum. The i18n supports also makes it extremely easy to translate the forum into languages that are
			not yet included in the main distribution.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The i18n support is accomplished by keeping all of the text displayed on the forum in a special file, which
			can be edited via this control panel or manually with a text editor.
			
			<note>
				<simpara>
				If you are introducing major changes or translating a forum in to another language you're probably
				better off making the modifications using a text editor rather then the web control panel. If you
				do translate the forum to another language keep in mind that in accordance with the &gpl; license
				you MUST provide us, FUDforum Development Team, with the translated text.
				</simpara>
			</note>
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The message editor displays a color coded view of the templates and their corresponding messages. It also
			indicated which files utilize each template.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Below is the explanation for the color codes used in the message editor.	
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Red</emphasis> Template name, clicking on this link will pull up a form with all the messages inside this template, allowing you to edit them.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Green</emphasis> Indicated a particular message. Clicking on this link will allow you to edit this message.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Brown</emphasis> These links are shown below the templates (in red) that are used by other templates. Clicking on this link will change your browser's focus to that template.</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		
		<para>
			When you click on the 'Edit' button available on the message edit form, your changes will be saved to the message
			file and the forum will be recompiled to using the new data you've entered.
		</para>
		
		<important>
			<simpara>
			After making manual modifications to the message file, click on the <link linkend="admin.rebuild_templates">Rebuild Templates</link>
			option in the admin control panel to activate the changes you have made.
			</simpara>
		</important>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.language">
		<title>Language Selection</title>
		
		<para>
			This option allows you to change the language your forum is in. The supported languages are listed in 
			the 'Language' select box.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.language.locale">
			<title>Locale</title>
			
			<para>
				Each language has a related locale value, the locale setting tells PHP to print all dynamically
				generated information such as dates in the selected language. This value is filled in automatically
				for you when you choose a language, if for whatever reason you believe the value is invalid or have a
				more appropriate locale value you can alter the default by entering a different value inside the 'Locale'
				textbox.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				If you are unsure of what this option does, it is better to leave the default value as the locale
				setting.
			</para>
			
			<note>
				<simpara>
				On most *NIX computers you can see the list supported locales by executing this command: 
				<literal>locale -a</literal>
				</simpara>
			</note>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.rebuild_templates">
		<title>Rebuild Templates</title>
		
		<para>
			This control will rebuild the forum's files from the templates. It is advised to run this utility 
			after performing any manual modifications to the forum's template, message or source files.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.smilies">
		<title>Smiley Manager</title>
		
		<para>
			This control panel allows the administrator to manage the smilies/emoticons supported by the forum.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.smilies.upload">
			<title>Smilies Upload</title>
			
			<para>
				At the top of the Smiley Manager control panel there is an upload control allowing the administrator
				to upload images from their hard drive that can be used as smilies.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Clicking on the 'Browse' button will open a dialog window using which an image can be selected. Once
				that is done, clicking the 'Upload' button will upload the image to the server placing it inside the
				smilies directory.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Once a smiley is uploaded, it's name will automatically be inserted into the 'Smiley Image' textbox
				and the preview of the smiley will be visible in the 'Preview Image'.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<para>
			This >Smilies Management control panel allows the administrator to add or edit existing smilies.
			At the time of editing all of the smiley's properties will be loaded into this control panel so that
			they may be edited.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.smilies.descr">
			<title>Smiley Description</title>
			
			<para>
				This text will appear in the alt tag of the smiley image, which would be shown if a user holds their
				mouse above the smiley image. For people using text only browsers this description will appear instead
				of the smiley image.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.smilies.code">
			<title>Smiley Text</title>
			
			<para>
				In this text field you enter the special code(s) that will be replaced by the smiley. You can enter
				more then one code by separating the codes with the <literal>~</literal> character.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.smilies.file">
			<title>Smiley Image</title>
			
			<para>
				The codes specified in the 'Smiley Text' option will be replaced with this image. You may choose the
				image from the available smilies by clicking on the 'SELECT ICON' link, which will pop-up a window
				will all the smiley images in the forum. You can choose the image you want by clicking on it.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.smilies.preview">
			<title>Preview Image</title>
			
			<para>
				The preview of image you've selected in the 'Smiley Image' option.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					The preview will not appear if you manually enter the image filename in the 'Smiley Image' option.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<para>
			At the bottom of the 'Smiley Manager' there is a list of all the smilies that are supported by the forum. Beside
			each smiley there are 3 control links allowing the administrator to change the smiley settings.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.smilies.edit">
			<title>Edit Link</title>
			
			<para>
				When clicked, this link will load the smiley information into 'Smilies Management' control allowing 
				the administrator to edit smiley's properties.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.smilies.del">
			<title>Delete Link</title>
			
			<para>
				Clicking on this link will remove the smiley from the system.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					The image will still be on the server, so that messages which use it will not have broken images
					in them. The image itself can be deleted manually via the shell or FTP and can also be removed 
					via the <link linkend="admin.file_manager">forum's file manager</link>.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.smilies.post">
			<title>Change Position Link</title>
			
			<para>
				Clicking this link will allow the administrator to change the position of the smiley. Normally the 
				smilies are displayed in the order they are added in to the system. This is important if you have 
				more smilies then you want to display shortcuts to on the post forms as defined by the 
				<link linkend="global.option.MAX_SMILIES_SHOWN">Maximum Smilies Shown</link> option in the global
				control panel.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				If that is the case only the first 'Maximum Smilies Shown' number of smilies will be shown on the post
				form and for the rest the user will need to click on a special link.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.forum_icons">
		<title>Forum Icon Manager</title>
		
		<para>
			This control panels allows the administrator to add and remove forum icons. Forum icons are images that
			the admin can choose to display beside each forum that they create.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.msg_icons">
		<title>Message Icon Manager</title>
		
		<para>
			This control panel allows the administrator to add and remove message icons. Message icons are images that
			the users may choose to use as icons of the messages that they post.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.avatar_apr">
		<title>Avatar Approval</title>
		
		<para>
			This form allows the administrator to approve any URL &amp; Uploaded avatars that forum users wish to use.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			If the uploaded image has greater dimensions then the ones specified as allowed and 
			<link linkend="global.option.MOGRIFY_BIN">mogrify tool</link> is available the administrator may choose to scale the 
			image down to <link linkend="global.option.CUSTOM_AVATAR_MAX_DIM">maximum allowed dimensions</link> by clicking on the 'Fix It' link.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.avatar">
		<title>Avatar Manager</title>
		
		<para>
			Allows the administrator to manager built-in forum avatars. These images can be used by the users as their avatars,
			unlike the URL &amp; Uploaded avatars these do not require administrator's approval before they are activated.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.avatar.upload">
			<title>Uploading Avatar</title>
			
			<para>
				At the top of the Avatar Manager form there is an upload control that would allow the administrator
				to upload new avatar in to the system.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				To select the image, click on the 'Browse' button, which will open a file selection dialog using which
				the administrator may choose an image from their drive that will be uploaded.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				Once the image is selected, clicking on the 'Upload' button will upload the avatar. Once uploaded, the
				file name of the avatar will appear inside the 'Avatar Image' text box and preview of the avatar will be
				available inside the 'Preview Image' control.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<para>
			Avatar Management form, which appears below the avatar upload form allows the administrator to edit and add avatars.
			During editing the avatar's values are inserted in to the form to allow for easy editing.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.avatar.descr">
			<title>Description</title>
			
			<para>
				A short description of the avatar, this text will appear below the avatar on the user's avatar selection
				form.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.avatar.img">
			<title>Avatar Image</title>
			
			<para>
				The filename of the avatar, you can choose an avatar from the list of available images by clicking on the
				adjacent 'SELECT AVATAR' link.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.avatar.preview">
			<title>Preview Image</title>
			
			<para>
				Shows the preview of the avatar.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<para>
			At the bottom of the page there is a list of all the available avatars. Beside each avatar there is an edit 
			and delete link allowing the administrator to edit this avatar's properties or delete it all together.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.email_filter">
		<title>Email filter</title>
		
		<para>
			Allows the administrator to block people with a matching e-mail address from posting messages on the forum. It 
			would also prevent people who's e-mail matches the filter, from registering on the forum.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.email_filter.simple">
			<title>Simple</title>
			
			<para>
				Use this filter if you are entering a specific e-mail address. ex. myemail@emaildomain.com
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="admin.email_filter.regex">
			<title>Regular Expression</title>
			
			<para>
				Use this filter if you want to use regular expression masks to match the e-mail address'. This is
				very useful if you want to block all people from a certain ISP. ex. .*@aol\.com filter would block
				all people who's e-mail address ends with @aol.com
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					Internally this function uses preg_match() to evaluate the regular expression.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.ip_filter">
		<title>IP Filter</title>
		
		<para>
			Allows the administrator to block people with a matching ip address' from posting messages on the forum.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The IP address can be entered in 2 ways:
			
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Complete IP</emphasis> 
					The full IP of the user, ex. 111.11.1.111 would block all user's who's IP is 111.11.1.111
				</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">IP Mask</emphasis> 
					You can enter an IP mask that would block a whole range of IP addresses
					<screen>ex. 22.23.24. IP mask would block all users who's first 3 IP elements are 22.23.24 or more commonly known as 22.23.24.0/24 mask.</screen>
					<screen>ex. 24.*.21.22 IP mask would block all users who's 1st IP element is 24 and the last 2 IP elements are 21.21</screen>
				</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.login_filter">
		<title>Login Filter</title>
		
		<para>
			Allows the administrator to block people with a matching login name from registering and posting messages on the forum.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			This option uses regular expression, so you can enter masks in this field. ex. .*fool.* would block people who's
			login contain the text <literal>fool</literal>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.file_filter">
		<title>File Filter</title>
		
		<para>
			Allows the administrator to specify which files types can be attached to forum messages. This is done by entering
			specifying the allowed file extensions.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			If no file extensions are listed then ANY file can be attached.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.dump">
		<title>Make forum datadump</title>
		
		<para>
			This option allows the administrator to generate a backup of all the forum data that is stored on disk
			and in MySQL. If PHP's gzip module is available the administrator may choose to compress the backed up data,
			to save drive space.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="admin.import">
		<title>Import forum data</title>
		
		<para>
			Import forum data from a forum datadump. It is recommended that the forum you're importing the data from
			and the forum you're importing the data to are of the same version.
			
			<warning>
				<simpara>
				Importing forum data would result in the loss of all current data inside the forum.
				</simpara>
			</warning>
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>