<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id: bugs.xml,v 1.1 2002/07/03 15:55:06 hackie Exp $ -->
<chapter id="bug_reports">
<title>Reporting Bugs</title>
	<para>
		Should you come across a bug inside &FUDforum; or a typo in the documentation please
		take a moment of your time and report it to the development team via 
		<ulink url="http://fud.prohost.org/forum/"><citetitle>Support Forum</citetitle></ulink> or
		by sending an <ulink url="mailto:forum@prohost.org"><citetitle>email</citetitle></ulink>.
	</para>
	
	<sect1 id="bug_reports.info">
		<title>Bug Information</title>
		
		<para>
			To ensure that your bug is solved quickly please include as much information as possible
			about the bug itself as well as your system configuration. Also, check on the 
			<ulink url="http://fud.prohost.org/forum/"><citetitle>Support Forum</citetitle></ulink>
			if any similar bugs were already posted and if a solution is already available in the later release
			or in the CVS.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="bug_reports.info.bug">
			<title>Bug</title>
			
			<para>
				Please include any warning &amp; error messages that occurred as the result of bug. If you
				had not received any such messages, please verify you php configuration to see that such
				errors would be displayed. This can be done make making sure that
				<emphasis type="bold">display_errors</emphasis> option is turn on and your 
				<emphasis type="bold">error_reporting</emphasis> option is set to E_ALL^E_NOTICE (2039) or
				greater.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				If the bug results in broken functionality please clearly explain the problem caused by the bug.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				You should always include the URL of the page where the bug had occurred even if the URL
				is not accessible via the Internet. The URL would let us know which page caused the problem
				and what variables may have been responsible for the problem you've experienced.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="bug_reports.info.system">
			<title>System Information</title>
			
			<para>
				A good bug report should also include information about the system on which the bug had occurred.
				The optimal way to get this information is by including the output of PHP's phpinfo() function
				in your bug report by making a small test script like this: 
				<screen><?php phpinfo(); ?></screen>
			</para>
			
			<para>
				If you cannot send us the phpinfo() output, please include the information shown by the
				<link linkend="admin.system_info">System Info</link> admin form as well as information about
				your browser.
			</para>
		</sect2>	
	</sect1>
</chapter>
