<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id: features.xml,v 1.8 2002/08/05 15:05:33 hackie Exp $ -->
<chapter id="features">
	<title>&FUDforum; Features</title>
	
	<para>
		&FUDforum; includes numerous features. This chapter will briefly overview most of those features to give you 
		an idea about the full capabilities of &FUDforum;.
	</para>
	
	<sect1 id="features.spell">
		<title>Spell Checker</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; supports a fully functional spell checker, that <link linkend="global.option.SPELL_CHECK_ENABLED">if 
			enabled</link> would allow forum users to spell check their messages before posting.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The spell checker utilizes PHP's Pspell library and supports multiple languages.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.template">
		<title>Templating System</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; contains a fully customizable templating system, that allows you to completely customize the the look
			and feel of your forum. For optimal performance the templates are compiled, so you do not lose any speed as you do 
			in other forums by having a templating system.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The <link linkend="admin.template_editor">Template Editor</link> can be found inside the administrator control panel.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.i18n">
		<title>i18n Support</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; has full &url.i18n; support, that allows an easy translation of the forum into a language of your choice.
			Currently &FUDforum; is distributed with 8 languages: English, French, German, Swedish, Polish, Turkish, Spanish and Chinese.
		</para>
		
		<para>	
			More languages will be available in the near future. During the installation process you will have the opportunity to
			choose the forum's language. This option can later be modified via the &FUDforum; 
			<link linkend="admin.theme_manager">Theme Manager</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.groups">
		<title>Group Permission System</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; supports a highly capable permissions system, which can be used to control what forum users can and cannot do.
			Using this system you can grant special access rights to certain users, block users from seeing and/or accessing certain
			forum etc.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			This system also includes support for "group managers" who have the ability to manage users in the groups they control. This
			option allows the admininistrator to delegate responsibility to trustworthy forum members.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The Group Management is done via two control panels. The first control panel is the <link linkend="admin.group_control_panel">administrative group manager</link>, which allows 
			admininistrator(s) to add/remove groups as well as assign group managers and specify what permissions the group managers can assign
			and/or take away. This control panel also allows the administrator to make groups inherit permissions from other groups,
			which eliminates the need to specify new permission every time for similar groups.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The second control panel, the <link linkend="mod.groups">user group manager</link>, which allows the group manager(s) 
			and the admininistrator(s) to add and remove users from a group as well as set permissions for individual users.
			It can be a accessed via a link available to all Administrators and Group Managers on most forum pages.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.pm">
		<title>Private Messaging</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; includes a private messaging (PM) system that <link linkend="global.option.PM_ENABLED">if enabled</link> via 
			the <link linkend="admin.global_settings_manager">global control panel</link> allows forum members to send private 
			messages to one another. 
		</para>
		
		<para> 
			The private messaging system supports forwarding, the ability to send a message to multiple users and reply notifications.
			If allowed by the administrator, the users may also attach one or more files to their private messages.
			Just like in a mail client the sent messages are stored in a special folder, 'sent', 
			so that the user can easily refer back to them if the need arises. There is also a 'drafts' folder
			where the user can keep their unfinished messages.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Via the <link linkend="global.pm.options">private messaging controls</link> administrator(s) can specify what 
			features the users may use inside their private messages, as well as the amount messages the users can 
			keep in their PM folders.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.files">
		<title>File Attachments</title>
		
		<para>
			If permitted by the administrator, users may attach files to their forum &amp; private messages. The amount of files that the user 
			can attach as well as their maximum size can be defined by the administrator on a forum by forum basis via the 
			<link linkend="admin.category_forum_management">forum control panel</link>. The ability to attach files to private messages can be defined by the administrator
			via the <link linkend="global.pm.options">private messaging system controls</link>.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			In addition to specifying the size and the quantity limits the administrator may also indicate what file types
			can be attached to the messages using the <link linkend="admin.file_filter">file attachment control panel</link>. 
			The attached files will be matched against the <link linkend="admin.mime_managment_system">&FUDforum; MIME listing</link> 
			so that (1) a proper file icon can be assigned to the file, (2) the file download form can send the proper 
			header to the browser, and (3) the browser can interpret the file properly.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			It is also possible to restrict certain users from being able to attach files or only allow certain users to attach files
			using the <link linkend="mod.groups">group management system</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.polls">
		<title>Polls</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; supports a complete polling system, which mnay enable users to add polls to their messages.
			Permissions to create and vote on polls is controlable by the admins via the 
			<link linkend="mod.groups">group management system</link>.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Polls contain multiple choice questions, which can be used to gather user opinions on poll issues or questions.
			The forum tracks the votes and ensures that people cannot vote more then once to prevent ballot stuffing.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.subscriptions">
		<title>Forum &amp; Topic Subscriptions</title>
		
		<para>
			The users on the forum have the ability to subscribe to topics &amp; forums. By subscribing to a topic a user will receive 
			an E-mail or ICQ notification about any new posts made inside that topic. The subscription to a forum on the other hand 
			will notify the user of any new topics created in the forum.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			To prevent sending multiple notifications the notification system will only notify the user if they have no unread 
			notifications for that particular forum or topic. This is extremely useful for active forums where many messages can be
			posted in a short period of time causing a massive amount of notifications to be sent to the user about the same content.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Each forum member has access to a personal subscription control panel, which can be used to see what 
			subscriptions they currently have and allow the user to unsubscribe from any of the subscribed to content.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			If specified by the administrator, the forum can include the full body of the message in the E-mail notification, so that a user
			can read and reply to the message directly via their mail client. These notifications come specially formated, so that
			they are properly displayed on all e-mail clients, regardless of whether those mail clients support HTML or not.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.tree">
		<title>Tree View</title>
		
		<para>
			In addition to the standard way of viewing messages inside the forum, &FUDforum; supports a tree view, which builds a tree
			of messages akin to the one used by the newsgroups.
		</para>
		
		<example>
			<title>Sample Tree View</title>
<screen>
[*] Main Message
	[-] Reply To: Main Message
	[+] Reply To: Main Message
		[+] Reply To: Reply To: Main Message
			[-] Reply To: Reply To: Reply To: Main Message
	[-] Another Reply to Main Message		
</screen>
		</example>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.search">
		<title>Full Text Search</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; includes a full text search that allows users to search the posted messages by entering one or more
			keywords. The user has the option of limiting the search to a particular forum or category or they can search the entire 
			forum. A user may either limit a search to a particular forum or category or search the entire forum.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The search form allows the user to specify whether to use the strict AND logic, which will find only
			the messages containing all of the specified keywords. Or to use the more relaxed OR logic, which will
			find any message that matches at least one of the specified terms in the query.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The search results can be sorted by date, allowing the user to specify whether the most recent messages
			should be shown first or last.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.ispy">
		<title>I-Spy &amp; Online Status</title>
		
		<para>
			I-SPY is a neat feature, that <link linkend="admin.action_log_viewer">if enabled</link> will allow forum 
			users to see what other forum users are doing at this very moment.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The forum also keeps track of the currently online users, an indicator is placed beside each message showing whether the author of the
			message is currently online or not. This too can be disabled via the <link linkend="admin.action_log_viewer">global control panel</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.fudcode">
		<title>FUDcode</title>
		
		<para>
			FUDcode is a series of text formatting tags that allow users to style the text of their messages &amp; signatures.
			More information about these features as well as the complete list of supported tags can be found 
			<link linkend="fudcode">here</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.smilies">
		<title>Smilies/Emoticons</title>
		
		<para>
			Smilies are commonly used codes to represent emotions, such as :-) to indicate happiness. 
			&FUDforum; has a list of  30 commonly uses smiley codes that will be replaced with image representing the corresponding 
			emotion the author is trying to convey. The administrator can add/edit/delete the supported smilies via the 
			<link linkend="admin.smilies">smilies control panel</link>.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Whether or not text codes are replaced with corresponding images can be defined by the administrator on a forum by 
			forum basis. The group management system can also be used to disallow usage of smilies.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.avatars">
		<title>Avatars</title>
		
		<para>
			If permitted by the administrator, users may choose to associate an avatar image with their posts and messages.
			Users may upload an image of their choice to the server, specify a URL to an image or
			selecting a file from their harddrive or choosing an image from the forum's built-in avatar
			galleries. The avatar images will be displayed beside the user's name on all of user's posts.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.custom_tags">
		<title>Custom Tags</title>
		
		<para>
			In &FUDforum; the administrator can assign users an unlimited number custom tags that 
			would appear on user's profile and beside user's posts. This feature can be used to 
			indicate any special roles or functions of the user.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Custom tags can be added or removed via the <link linkend="admin.user_manager">user control panel</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.ranks">
		<title>User Ranks</title>
		
		<para>
			User Ranks are assigned to users based on the number of posts they have made on the forum. 
			These ranks may contain a text and or image indicator showing the user's rank.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The administrator can add, edit, or delete the available user ranks via the <link linkend="admin.ranks">rank manager</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.censor">
		<title>Censor &amp; Replacement System</title>
		
		<para>
			In &FUDforum; the administrator can specify that certain words or strings will be replaced automatically by 
			alternatives provided by the administrator. This is most commonly used to filter inappropriate language 
			that the administrator does not want to allow in the forum.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The administrator can specify the strings that are to be replaced via the 
			<link linkend="admin.replacement_censorship_system">replacement control panel</link>, which supports 
			both basic replacement and regex pattern matching.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.iptracking">
		<title>IP Tracking</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; tracks the IP addresses of all users as they submit posts to the forum. Administrators and forum moderators
			can see the IP address of the author beside each message. In addition, the IP address 
			itself is a link to a URL that will attempt to look up the ISP of the user who 
			submitted the post or message.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.actionlog">
		<title>Action Log</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; logs all actions taken by privileged users such as moderators. The 
			<link linkend="admin.action_log_viewer">action log</link> allows administrator(s) to see 
			time-stamped details of actions that have been taken by users with special privileges. 
			The action log will also show all failed attempts to login to the administrator account.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.message_mangling">
		<title>Message Mangling</title>
		
		<para>
			Message mangling refers to the ability to edit, delete, move and split
			topics and messages. Administrators may grant message mangling permissions 
			to moderators and other users.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.user_block">
		<title>User Blocking</title>
		
		<para>
			The administrator has an extensive set of tools to block people from the forum. 
			The tools include an <link linkend="admin.ip_filter">IP filter</link> 
			to block access to FUDforum from any IP address or IP address mask.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <link linkend="admin.email_filter">e-mail filter</link> blocks all users who's e-mail address 
			matches the mask specified by the administrator. The e-mail filter also prevents
			new registrations using an e-mail that matches the specified mask.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <link linkend="admin.login_filter">Login filter</link>, blocks all users who's login 
			matches the mask specified by the administrator. The login filter also prevents people
			from registering with a login that matches the specified mask.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.sessions">
		<title>Session Support</title>
		
		<para>
			If cookies are not enabled on the user's computer, &FUDforum; will use URL sessions
			to keep track of the user. This allows use of the forum even if cookies are not 
			supported or allowed on the users computer.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.mlist_nntp">
		<title>Mailing List &amp; NNTP Integration</title>
		
		<para>
			FUDforum includes tools which will allow the forum to be used to
			archive newsgroups (NNTP) and mailing lists. In addition, FUDforum
			allows the administrator to permit forum members to post messages back
			to a mailing list or a newsgroup. This feature makes FUDforum an ideal
			access point to newsgroups and mailing lists for those who cannot
			access those resources directly.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.installation">
		<title>Installation &amp; Upgrade</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; includes an installation wizard that is so easy to use,
			it will have your forum up and running within minutes. The upgrade
			process is even easier. Simply download the upgrade pack from the
			<ulink url="http://fud.prohost.org/"><citetitle>&FUDforum; website</citetitle></ulink> 
			and run the script, which will automatically perform all necessary upgrades from 
			any previous version.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.php">
		<title>PHP Related Features</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; can be successfully installed on systems configured with
			PHP safe_mode enabled and those which may have the register_globals
			and magic_quotes_gpc parameters turned off.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.speed">
		<title>Forum Speed</title>
	                      
	        <para>
			Despite its many features, FUDforum 2.3 is still extremely fast. It is
			probably faster than all the other forum applications that offer
			similar or even lesser feature sets. FUDforums excellent performance
			is the result of highly tuned interfaces to the underlying MySQL or
			PostgreSQL database and highly optimized PHP code.
	        </para>
	        
	        <para>
			In most cases, the forum will generate a page in less than one tenth
			(0.1) of a second.
	        </para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.security">
		<title>Security</title>
		
		<para>
			Security is an often overlooked feature in web based applications. As
			a result, many web based applications have large security holes that
			even the most incompetent hacker can exploit, causing a great deal of
			damage and annoyance.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Considerable care has been taken to ensure that, given the available
			programming tools, the default installation of the FUDforum 2.3 is
			designed to offer the greatest possible security. It would be very
			difficult if not impossible for a curious user or even a hacker to
			access your sensitive data.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			To achieve this level of security, by default &FUDforum; stores
			files using the least possible file permissions (0600 for files and
			0700 for directories), which allow only the user account under which
			the web server is running to access FUDforum's files.
			
			<note>
				<simpara>
				On servers that are configured to appropriately switch users for each
				virtual host (like Apache 2.x) your forum files will be even more
				secure because they will be accessible by you alone.
				</simpara>
			</note>
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Although you may think that giving a web server to ownership of the files is
			equivalent to allowing access to anyone, that is simply not the case.
			On a secure server, for example, the administrator should implement a
			PHP open_basedir limitation to restrict PHP scripts from accessing
			files in directories not owned by a current virtual host, thus
			preventing access through PHP to source code &amp; data files of FUDforum.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			On a properly configured server, any programs running within the CGI
			wrapper should not be able to access your files because (if a proper
			suid interface has been implemented by the server administrator)
			programs within the CGI wrapper should run as the user who executed them.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Consequently, given a well set up server, the forum's data should be
			quite secure, even on a shared hosting platform.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
