<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id: features.xml,v 1.3 2002/07/02 15:06:04 hackie Exp $ -->
<chapter id="features">
	<title>&FUDforum; Features</title>
	
	<para>
		&FUDforum; includes numerous features, this section will briefly overview most of those features to give you 
		an idea about the full capabilities of &FUDforum;.
	</para>
	
	<sect1 id="features.spell">
		<title>Spell Checker</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; supports a fully functional spell checker, that <link linkend="global.option.SPELL_CHECK_ENABLED">if 
			enabled</link> would allow forum users to spell check their messages before posting.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The spell checker utilizes PHP's Pspell library and supports multiple languages.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.template">
		<title>Templating System</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; contains a fully customizable templating system, that allows you to completely customize the the look
			and feel of your forum. For optimal performance the templates are compiled, so you do loose any speed as you do 
			in other forums by having a templating system.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The <link linkend="admin.template_editor">controls for the templating system</link> can be found inside 
			the admin control panel.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.i18n">
		<title>i18n Support</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; has full i18n support, that allows an easy translation of the forum into a language of your choice.
			Currently &FUDforum; is distributed with 7 languages: English, German, Swedish, Polish, Turkish, Spanish and Chinese.
		</para>
		
		<para>	
			More languages will be available in the near future. During the installation process you will have the opportunity to
			choose the forum's language. This option can later be modified via the &FUDforum; 
			<link linkend="admin.theme_manager">Theme Manager</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.groups">
		<title>Group Permission System</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; supports a highly capable permissions system, which can be used to control what forum users can and cannot do.
			Using this system you can grant special access rights to certain users, block users from seeing and/or accessing certain
			forum etc... 
		</para>
		
		<para>
			This system also includes support for "group managers" have the ability to manage users in the groups they control. This
			option allows the admin to delegate responsibility to trustworthy forum members.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The Group Management is done via two control panels, the <link linkend="admin.group_control_panel">administrative group manager</link>, which allows 
			the admin(s) to add/remove groups as well as assign group managers and specify what permissions the group managers can assign
			and/or take away. This control panel also allows the admin to make groups inherit permissions from other groups, thus not 
			needing to specify new permission every time for similar groups.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The second control panel, the <link linkend="mod.groups">user group manager</link>, which allows the group manager(s) 
			and the admin(s) to add and remove users from a group as well as change the permissions of the users inside the group 
			can be a accessed via a link available to all Administrators and Group Managers on most forum pages.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.pm">
		<title>Private Messaging</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; includes a private messaging system that <link linkend="global.option.PM_ENABLED">if enabled</link> via 
			the <link linkend="admin.global_settings_manager">global control panel</link> allows forum members to send private 
			messages to one another. 
		</para>
		
		<para> 
			The private messaging system supports forwarding, the ability to send a message to multiple users and reply notifications.
			If allowed by the administrator, the users may also attach one or more files to their private messages.
			Just like in a mail client the sent messages are stored in a special folder, 'sent', 
			so that the user can easily refer back to them if the need arises. There is also a 'drafts' folder
			where the user can keep their unfinished messages.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The admin via the <link linkend="global.pm.options">private messaging controls</link> can specify what features the users
			may use inside their private messages, as well as the amount messages the users can keep in their PM folders.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.files">
		<title>File Attachments</title>
		
		<para>
			If permitted by the admin users may attach files to their forum &amp; private messages. The amount of files that the user 
			can attach as well as their maximum size can be defined by the admin on a forum by forum basis via the 
			<link linkend="admin.category_forum_management">forum control panel</link>. The ability to attach files to private messages can be defined by the admin
			via the <link linkend="global.pm.options">private messaging system controls</link>.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			In addition to specifying the size and the quantity limits the administrator may also indicate what file types
			can be attached to the messages using the <link linkend="admin.file_filter">file attachment control panel</link>. 
			The attached files will be matched against the <link linkend="admin.mime_managment_system">&FUDforum; MIME listing</link> 
			so that a proper file icon can be assigned to the file as well as allowing the file download form to send the 
			proper header to the browser allowing it to interpret the file properly.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			It is also possible to restrict certain users from being able to attach files or only allow certain users to attach files
			using the <link linkend="mod.groups">group management system</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.polls">
		<title>Polls</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; supports a complete polling system, which allows users, if permitted to add polls to their messages.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Polls are quick multiple choice questioners, which can be used to gather user options on a matter at hand. The forum tracks
			the votes and ensures that people cannot vote more then once to prevent ballot stuffing.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.subscriptions">
		<title>Forum &amp; Thread Subscriptions</title>
		
		<para>
			The users on the forum have the ability to subscribe to threads &amp; forums. By subscribing to a thread a user will receive 
			an E-mail or ICQ notification about any new posts made inside that thread. The subscription to a forum on the other hand 
			will notify the user of any new threads created in the forum.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			To prevent sending multiple notifications the notification system will only notify the user if they have no unread 
			notifications for that particular forum or thread. This is extremely useful for active forums where many messages can be
			posted in a short period of time causing a massive amount of notifications to be sent to the user about the same content.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Each forum member has access to their own subscription control panel, which can be used to see what subscriptions they
			currently have and allow the user to unsubscribe from any of the subscribed to content.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			If specified by the admin, the forum can include the full body of the message in the E-mail notification, so that a user
			can read and reply to the message directly via their mail client. These notifications come specially formated, so that
			they are properly displayed on all e-mail clients, regardless of whether those mail clients support HTML or not.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.tree">
		<title>Tree View</title>
		
		<para>
			In addition to the standard way of viewing messages inside the forum, &FUDforum; supports a tree view, which builds a tree
			of messages akin to the one used by the newsgroups.
		</para>
		
		<example>
			<title>Sample Tree View</title>
<screen>
[*] Main Message
	[-] Reply To: Main Message
	[+] Reply To: Main Message
		[+] Reply To: Reply To: Main Message
			[-] Reply To: Reply To: Reply To: Main Message
	[-] Another Reply to Main Message		
</screen>
		</example>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.search">
		<title>Full Text Search</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; includes a full text search that allows users to search the posted messages by entering on or more
			keywords. The user has the option of limiting the search to a particular forum or category or they can search the entire 
			forum. In addition the user may specify whether to search the in the entire message or just in the message subject.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.ispy">
		<title>I-Spy &amp; Online Status</title>
		
		<para>
			I-SPY is a neat feature, that <link linkend="admin.action_log_viewer">if enabled</link> will allow forum 
			users to see what other forum users are doing at this very moment.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The forum also keeps track of the currently online users, and indicator is placed beside each message showing whether the author of the
			message is currently online or not. This too can be disabled via the <link linkend="admin.action_log_viewer">global control panel</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.fudcode">
		<title>FUDcode</title>
		
		<para>
			FUDcode is a series of text formatting tags that allow users to style the text of their messages &amp; signatures.
			More information about this features as well as the complete list of supported tags can be found 
			<link linkend="fudcode">here</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.smilies">
		<title>Smilies/Emoticons</title>
		
		<para>
			Smilies are commonly used codes to represent emotions, such as :) for example is generally used to indicate happiness. 
			&FUDforum; has a list of  30 commonly uses smiley codes that will be replaced with image representing the corresponding 
			emotion the author is trying to convey. The administrator can add/edit/delete the supported smilies via the 
			<link linkend="admin.smilies">smilies control panel</link>.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Whether or not text codes are replaced with corresponding images can be defined by the administrator on a forum by 
			forum basis. The group management system can also be used to disallow usage of smilies.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.avatars">
		<title>Avatars</title>
		
		<para>
			If permitted by the administrator users can choose to have an avatar image which they can either upload to the server,
			specify a url to or choose from the forum's avatar galleries. The avatar images will be displayed beside their name
			on all of their posts.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.custom_tags">
		<title>Custom Tags</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; allows the administrator to assign users an unlimited number custom tags that 
			would appear on their profile as well as beside their posts. This feature can be used to 
			indicate any special functions of the user.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Custom tags can be added or removed via the <link linkend="admin.user_manager">user control panel</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.ranks">
		<title>User Ranks</title>
		
		<para>
			User Ranks are assigned to users based on the number of posts they have made on the forum. These ranks may contain
			a text and/or image indicator showing the user's rank.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The administrator can add/edit/delete the available user ranks via the <link linkend="admin.ranks">rank manager</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.censor">
		<title>Censor &amp; Replacement System</title>
		
		<para>
			In &FUDforum; you can specify that certain strings or words would be replaced by the alternatives provided by
			the administrator. This is most commonly used to filter in appropriate language from being used in the forum.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The administrator can specify the strings that are to be replaced via the 
			<link linkend="admin.replacement_censorship_system">replacement control panel</link>, which supports 
			both basic replacement as well as regex pattern matching.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.iptracking">
		<title>IP Tracking</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; tracks the IP address of all the people who have made posts on the forum. The moderators &amp; administrators
			can see the IP of the author beside each message posted. In addition to showing the IP, the IP itself is a link to a URL
			that shows the ISP of the person who's IP this is.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.actionlog">
		<title>Action Log</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; logs all the actions taken by privileged users such as moderators. The 
			<link linkend="admin.action_log_viewer">action log</link> allows the administrator(s) to see when and what 
			actions were performed by the users with special privileges. This form will also show the log 
			of all the failed login attempts in to the administrator account.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.message_mangling">
		<title>Message Mangling</title>
		
		<para>
			The ability to edit, delete, move and split threads and messages.	
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.user_block">
		<title>User Blocking</title>
		
		<para>
			The administrator has an extensive set of tools to block people from the forum. This includes and 
			<link linkend="admin.ip_filter">IP filter</link> that allows blockage of users with a certain IP mask from accessing the forum.
		</para>
		<para>
			<link linkend="admin.email_filter">Email filter</link>, blocks all users who's e-mail address matches the mask specified by the admin.
			This also prevents people from registering with an e-mail that matches the specified mask.
		</para>
		<para>
			<link linkend="admin.login_filter">Login filter</link>, block all users who's login matches the mask specified by the admin.
			This also prevents people from registering with a login that matches the specified mask.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.sessions">
		<title>Session Support</title>
		
		<para>
			If for whatever reason cookies are not enabled on the user's computer &FUDforum; will use URL sessions to 
			keep track of the user. Thus allowing the user use the forum even if they do not have a cookie set on their
			computer.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.installation">
		<title>Installation &amp; Upgrade</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; includes an easy to use installation wizard that will have your forum up and running within minutes. The upgrade
			process is even easier, simply download the upgrade pack from 
			<ulink url="http://fud.prohost.org/"><citetitle>&FUDforum; website</citetitle></ulink> and run the script,  
			this script will automatically perform the all necessary upgrades from any previous forum version.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.php">
		<title>PHP Related Features</title>
		
		<para>
			&FUDforum; can be successfully installed on systems with safe_mode enabled as well as PHP installations with register_globals 
			&amp; magic_quotes_gpc turned off.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.speed">
		<title>Forum Speed</title>
	                      
	        <para>
	        	Although not a feature per say, it should be noted that despite the many features &FUDforum; is still extremely fast, probably
	        	faster then all the other forums that offer similar and even lesser feature sets. This is accomplished by a very highly tuned
	        	MySQL or PostgreSQL interface as well as a very optimized PHP code.
	        </para>
	        
	        <para>
	        	The forum will in most cases not take more then 0.1 seconds to generate a page.
	        </para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="features.security">
		<title>Security</title>
		
		<para>
			Security is an often overlooked feature in many web based applications and as the result many 
			of those applications have large security holes that even the most incompetent of hackers can exploit
			and cause a great deal damage and annoyance.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			We've taken the time to ensure that the default installation of the &FUDforum; offers the greatest possible
			security given the available tools, to ensure that should your web server be reasonably secure it would be
			very difficult if not impossible for a curious user or even a hacker to access your sensitive data.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			To accomplish this task, &FUDforum; by default will store your files with the most minimalistic permissions
			possible (0600 for files and 0700 for directories), allowing only the user the web server is running on
			to access your files.
			
			<note>
				<simpara>
				On servers, which appropriately switch users for each virtual host, like Apache 2 this approach
				is even safer since all your forum's files would be accessible by you and you alone.
				</simpara>
			</note>
		</para>
		
		<para>
			You may think that allowing web server access to your files is equivalent to allowing anyone to
			access your files. That is simply not the case, on a secure server the administrator would have setup
			an 'open_basedir' PHP limitation that would have restricted php scripts from accessing files in directories
			not owned by a current virtual host, thus preventing people from using PHP to access files of other users.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			On a properly setup server any programs within the CGI wrapper would not be able to access your
			files as well since they would run as the user who had executed them if a proper suid interface had been
			setup by the server's administrator.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			So, given a well setup server, even on shared hosting solution your forum's data would be quite secure.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
