<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id: modopt.xml,v 1.1.1.1 2002/06/17 23:00:10 hackie Exp $ -->
<chapter id="mod_options">
	<title>Moderation Options</title>
	
	<para>
		&FUDforum; has a number of tools that are available to moderators and administrators in regard to managing users and
		messages, this section covers those tools and gives tips on how to use them to their maximum potential.		
	</para>
	
	<note>
		<simpara>
		When referring to 'privileged users', this section refers to users who are moderators, administrators
		and to the users who have been granted permission pertaining to a certain ability using the groups permissions
		system if a relevant permission is available.
		</simpara>
	</note>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.avatar">
		<title>Custom Avatar Queue</title>
		
		<para>
			This link will only be visible to the forum's administrator(s) should there be any custom avatars pending 
			approval. Beside the link there will be a red number indicating the number of avatars that are 
			pending administrative approval. Clicking on the link would take the administrator to the 
			<link linkend="admin.avatar_apr">avatar approval form</link> allowing them to approve or decline the avatar.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			If the avatar is approved or declined, the user who had requested this avatar will be notified via a private
			message if <link linkend="global.pm.options">private messaging system</link> is enabled or 
			via e-mail about the status of their avatar.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.msg">
		<title>Moderation Queue</title>
		
		<para>
			This link will be visible if there are any messages pending approval in <link linkend="forum.mod">moderated forums</link>. 
			Beside the link there would be a red indicator showing the number of messages awaiting approval. Clicking on the 
			link would take the moderator to a control panel where they would be able to see all of the messages that are 
			pending approval and either approve or delete those messages by using 'Approve' and 'Delete' links found on that
			page.
			
			<note>
				<simpara>
				This option is ONLY be visible to the administrator(s) and forum moderators who moderate the forums
				that have unapproved messages in them.
				</simpara>
			</note>
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.reported">
		<title>Reported Messages</title>
		
		<para>
			This link will be visible if there are any reported messages. Reported messages are messages that a forum user
			has chosen to report to the forum administration for whatever reason, as part of the report form the user will
			be required to enter a reason for the message report so that the administration staff knows why this report was
			made. 
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Clicking on the reported messages link will take the moderator to a special page where the moderator can review
			the reported message as well as reason for the report. From that page the moderator may choose to delete the 
			report and/or take some action in response to the report.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.move">
		<title>Move Thread</title>
		
		<para>
			This option which is visible to all privileged users beside each thread on the thread view (thread.php) allows
			them to move the thread to a different forum. Clicking on the link will open a pop-up window with a list of all
			the available forums.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			If the user in question has permission to move the thread to the destination forum then the thread will be moved
			to their forum of choice once they click on that forum.
		</para>
		
		<para>	
			 Otherwise beside the forum there will be a 'request a move' link. Clicking on this link will allow the moderator
			 to request that the thread be moved to another forum, the form will allow the moderator to enter their reasoning
			 behind their request. It will then be up to the administrator(s) or the moderator(s) of the destination forum
			 to approve or decline the request via the <link linkend="mod.thread_exchange">Thread Exchange</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.thread_exchange">
		<title> Thread Exchange</title>
		
		<para>
			This link will be visible if there are any move thread requests pending as well as indicate how many of those
			requests are pending. Clicking on the link would take the moderator to a page where they'll be able to see
			the move request and either accept or decline the move thread request made by another moderator.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.del">
		<title>Delete Threads/Messages</title>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.del.thread">
			<title>Deleting a thread</title>
			
			<para>
				Deletion of a thread is an action, which can be performed by privileged users by clicking on the delete
				link beside each thread on the thread listing, or by clicking on the delete button of the root 
				(1st message in the thread) message.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.del.msg">
			<title>Deleting a message</title>
			
			<para>
				Privileged users can delete a message by clicking on the delete button located at the bottom of each 
				message, that is located in a forum where they have delete privileges. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.edit">
		<title>Edit Message</title>
		
		<para>
			Privileged users can edit the content as well as the subject of the message posted in forums in which they have
			edit privileges.
			
			<note>
				<simpara>
				Unless the <link linkend="global.option.EDITED_BY_MOD">Show Edited By Moderator</link> is set to no, 
				messages edited by privileged users will be marked as such.
				</simpara>
			</note>
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.split">
		<title>Split Thread</title>
		
		<para>
			Split thread link, which is visible to privileged users when they are viewing the content of the thread allows
			for splitting of a thread in to two separate threads. This is mostly done to allow the forum staff to move 
			off topic discussions that have wondered in to a relevant thread.	
		</para>
		
		<para>
			When clicked, the link would take the privileged user to a control form where how the thread will be split
			can be specified.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			At the top of this form there is a textbox where the name of the new thread will be specified as well as a drop
			down box with a list of forums where the new thread will be placed. Below these controls there are two buttons
			allowing the privileged user to split the selected or the non-selected messages.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			All the messages in the thread are listed on the 'Split Thread Control Panel', the messages can be selected 
			by marking the checkbox, which is located to left of every message. 
		</para>	
					
		<para>
			Clicking on the 'Split selected messages' button would then split all the selected messages or if the 
			'Split non-selected messages' button is clicked then all the non-selected messages will be moved to a new thread.
		</para>	
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.lock">
		<title>Thread Locking/Unlocking</title>
		
		<para>
			Privileged users may lock and unlock threads using a link available on the thread contents page. Locked threads
			prevent regular users from being able to post replies in the thread.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			When privileged users post new threads or replies to existing threads they may lock thread by marking the
			'Thread Locked' checkbox. The thread will be automatically locked once the post is made.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.sticky">
		<title>Sticky/Announcements</title>
		
		<para>
			Privileged users may create threads and mark them as 'Sticky' or 'Announcements'. Such threads will be displayed
			at the top of thread listing regardless of their age until they reach their expiration date as defined by the
			privileged user.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			This functionality is available on the post form to all privileged users.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.ip">
		<title>Display of Message Author IP Address</title>
		
		<para>
			All moderators and administrators will be able to see the IP address of message authors. Clicking on the IP
			address will open a page, which will show the information about that user's ISP.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="mod.groups">
		<title>User Group Management</title>
		
		<para>
			This control panel allows the administrator(s) and <link linkend="admin.group_control_panel.leader">group leader(s)</link> to add 
			and remove users from the various groups as well as alter the permissions of those users.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			If the user can manage more then one group then a list of all the groups that they can manage will be shown
			allowing them to choose a group to edit.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The form also includes a control allowing for addition/editing of users in the group as well as specifying their
			permissions, the editable permissions contain drop downs with 'Yes/No' toggles allowing the group manager to
			grant or take away the permission from the user. 
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Below is the explanation of the permissions that can be granted or removed using the groups system.
		</para>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.visible">
			<title>Visible</title>
			
			<para>
				Allows the user to see the forum on the forum listing on the front page.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.read">
			<title>Read</title>
			
			<para>
				Allows the user to read the messages inside the forum.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.post">
			<title>Post</title>
			
			<para>
				The ability to create new threads in the forum.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.reply">
			<title>Reply</title>
			
			<para>
				The ability to post replies to existing threads in the forum.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.edit">
			<title>Edit</title>
			
			<para>
				The ability to edit messages posted by other users.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					Normally they users can only edit their own messages.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.delete">
			<title>Delete</title>
			
			<para>
				The ability to deletes threads &amp; posted by other users.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.sticky">
			<title>Sticky posts</title>
			
			<para>
				The ability to create <link linkend="mod.sticky">Sticky/Announcement</link> threads.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.polls">
			<title>Create polls</title>
			
			<para>
				The ability to add polls to messages posted on the forum.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.vote">
			<title>Votes</title>
			
			<para>
				Whether or not the user may vote on the polls in the forum.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					This option will ALWAYS be set to NO for anonymous users, since their uniqueness
					cannot be determined reliably.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.files">
			<title>Attach files</title>
			
			<para>
				Whether or not the user can attach file(s) to their messages.
				
				<note>	
					<simpara>
					If the number of allowed file attachments for the forum is set to 0, then
					even if this option is set to 'Yes' users will not be able to attach files.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.rate">
			<title>Rate threads</title>
			
			<para>
				Whether or not a user can rate threads inside the forum.
				<note>
					<simpara>
					This option will ALWAYS be set to NO for anonymous users, since their uniqueness
					cannot be determined reliably.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.split">
			<title>Split threads</title>
			
			<para>
				The ability to <link linkend="mod.split">split threads</link>.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.lock">
			<title>Lock threads</title>
			
			<para>
				The ability to <link linkend="mod.lock">lock &amp; unlock</link> threads in the forum.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					Users with this ability will also have the ability to post replies in locked threads.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.move">
			<title>Move threads</title>
			
			<para>
				The ability to <link linkend="mod.move">move or request that a thread be moved</link> to another forum.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.smilies">
			<title>Use smilies</title>
			
			<para>
				If enabled, the user's emoticon tags will be converted to equivalent smiley images during the posting
				process.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2 id="mod.groups.images">
			<title>Use image tags</title>
			
			<para>
				Whether or not this user may use &fudcode;'s [img] tags in their code.
				
				<note>
					<simpara>
					If the <link linkend="global.option.MAX_IMAGE_COUNT">maximum allowed images per message option</link> is set to 0 this option will have no affect.
					</simpara>
				</note>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
